<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Three sermons preached in the Cathedral Church of Winchester The first on Sunday, August. 19. 1660. at the first return of the Dean and Chapter to that church, after the restauration of His Majesty. The second on Jan. 30. 1661. being the anniversary of King Charles the first, of glorious memory. The third at the general assize held there, Feb. 25. 1661. By Edward Stanley, D.D. Prebendary of the church.</title>
            <author>Stanley, Edward, 1597 or 8-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 82 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93792</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5233D</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229852</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895536</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895536</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153008</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93792)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153008)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2340:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Three sermons preached in the Cathedral Church of Winchester The first on Sunday, August. 19. 1660. at the first return of the Dean and Chapter to that church, after the restauration of His Majesty. The second on Jan. 30. 1661. being the anniversary of King Charles the first, of glorious memory. The third at the general assize held there, Feb. 25. 1661. By Edward Stanley, D.D. Prebendary of the church.</title>
                  <author>Stanley, Edward, 1597 or 8-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 157, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J.G. for John Clark, at his shop under St. Peters church in Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With an initial imprimatur leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms XIV, 7 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Lamentations IIII, 20 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah I, 26 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Anglican authors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:153008:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Robertus Pory, <hi>S.T.P. Reverendiſsimo in Chriſto Patri, Domino</hi> Gulielmo <hi>Archiepiſcopo Cant. Sacellanus Domesticus.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153008:1"/>
            <p>THREE SERMONS <hi>PREACHED</hi> In the Cathedral Church of WINCHESTER.
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Firſt on Sunday,</hi> Aug. 19. 1660. <hi>at the firſt return of the Dean and Chapter to that Church, after the Reſtauration of His Majeſty.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Second on</hi> Jan. 30. 1661. <hi>being the Anniverſary of King</hi> Charles <hi>the First, of glorious memory.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Third at the general Aſsize held there,</hi> Feb. 25. 1661.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By EDWARD STANLEY, D.D. Prebendary of that Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>J.G.</hi> for <hi>John Clark,</hi> at his Shop under St. <hi>Peters</hi> Church in Cornhill, 1662.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:153008:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153008:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, and the Right Reverend Father in God, <hi>GEORGE,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter,</hi> and one of the Lords of His Majeſties moſt Honourable Privy Council.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THeſe Sermons were preached in your Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral, though be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was yours: And you will give me leave to take this occaſion to Congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late your coming thither. I wiſh your Lordſhip may ſit long at the Helm of Government there, and that you may find the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters untroubled. But the Church being yours now at the Printing of them, the Sermons ought to
<pb facs="tcp:153008:3"/>be yours too, if they were worth your owning, or a publick De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication.</p>
            <p>Such as they are I preſent them to your Lordſhip, and crave your Protection for the Author of them, for 'tis poſsible he may want it. And though they were not deſigned to be publick when they were preached by me, as you will find in the Preface, yet now they are ſo. If there be any <hi>Errata</hi> in them, as there may be ſome in Sermons of ſo haſty a Conception, as I aſſure your Lordſhip theſe were, you will be pleaſed to pardon them to</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt humble and moſt devoted Servant, <hi>EDWARD STANLEY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:153008:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Do not think there is any thing in theſe Sermons ſo worthy of the publick view, that they ſhould be thus expoſed, without ſome other Inducement for it. Neither can I ſay, they are publiſhed by ſpecial command, for they were preach'd far from Court. But two of them being commanded from me by a kind of neceſsity, and in my own defence, I was willing the third ſhould be caſt into the bargain, being all of them of kin, and the ſubject much the ſame. Thoſe which I underſtand my ſelf to be charged with are the two lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and peradventure there was as much fault found with the former; for we live in a Capricious Age, in which the Confines of ſin muſt not be touch'd,
<pb facs="tcp:153008:4"/>neither muſt we come near it, or tread, though never ſo gently, upon the utmoſt lines of it. The conception of theſe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons was ſomewhat haſty, and without any long preparation, therefore the more to be excuſed. The perſons concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned are not ſo, that have put me to this open Penance; who are ſo far from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance for their evil doings, that they are impatient of the moſt modeſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof of them.</p>
            <p>Whether there be any thing here, that was peccant againſt the rules of Charity or Sobriety, or that was unfit for me to ſpeak, or them to hear, I make thee the Judge.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153008:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Sermon preached in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral Church of <hi>Winche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> at the firſt return of the Dean and Chapter to that Church after the Reſtauration of His Majeſty.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 14.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quis dabit ex</hi> Sion <hi>ſalutare</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael? <hi>Cum averterit Dominus captivitatem plebis ſuae, exultabit</hi> Jacob, <hi>&amp; laetabitur</hi> Iſrael.</p>
                  <p>Who ſhall give ſalvation unto <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Sion?</hi> When the Lord turneth the captivity of his people, then ſhall <hi>Jacob</hi> rejoyce, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall be glad.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough I never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaired of Gods mercy to this poor Church and State, yet I durſt not promiſe my ſelf ſo much happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to ſee it; and I thought rather
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:153008:5"/>of writing my own Epitaph near a Pulpit, then of ſpeaking out of it any more in this place: Yet ſo the Divine Providence hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered it, that I ſhould out live the Storm in which thouſands have periſhed, that were more righteous then my ſelf. This is one of Chriſts miracles, that he hath ſtilled the raging of the Sea; that though we were unworthily caſt out, yet we are met again, <hi>in nave Eccleſiae:</hi> And whether it be the Quire, or the Body of the Church, it matters not; but here we are by Gods mercy, and the Ship it ſelf is, we hope, ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; though much torn and ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſack'd, as you ſee. Let God onely have the glory of it, while my firſt Sermon ſhall be a Thankſgiving; it ought to be ſo, not one Thankſgiving in a year, but it ſhould be a year of Jubilee's and Thankſgivings: For ſuch a Deliverance as we have had all
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153008:5"/>the dayes in the year would be too few.</p>
            <p>I will devote this to it, and confine my ſelf to that Subject; and this Text will ſupply me with fit materials, for it lands us at <hi>Exultabit</hi> Jacob, <hi>&amp; laetabitur</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael; The rejoycing of <hi>Iacob,</hi> and the gladneſs of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Gladneſs and Rejoycing is an Argument that hath been out of date with us for many years to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; our Harps have been hung upon the Trees that are therein, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137. nay,
'tis Gods mercy that we our ſelves have eſcaped it, and have been ſuffered to ſit weeping by the waters of <hi>Babylon;</hi> for we have been in a Captivity alſo. All that we could do for you was but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it, and to weep for it; and while we were unjuſtly char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with looking toward <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the cry was loud in every bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies ear, to come out of her, we
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153008:6"/>were carried into her whether we would or no; at leaſt we have had all the Temptations that could be to drive us thither; nay, have we not been forced to it <hi>Vi &amp; armis,</hi> while we have been dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from our Habitations, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd from our Houſes and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Poſſeſſions? And ſo if Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience had not kept us back, the neceſſity and wants of too many of us had been enough to fix us there. And yet, God be thanked, the Temptation is over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come; in ſpight of Malice it ſelf, and the Calumnies of wicked men, we are where we were ſtill at <hi>Sion,</hi> in our Judgments the ſame men, as to our Religion, though forced and driven away from it in our Perſons. We have been, I ſay, in a kind of Captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for a great many years, and all we could do was to look towards <hi>Sion,</hi> and, as <hi>Daniel</hi> did in his Chamber, the Windows being
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153008:6"/>open, to pray toward it; but to come at it, and to diſcharge our duties there, we were not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered.</p>
            <p>Well, after a long Captivity, you ſee, it hath pleaſed God to bring us hither again; and what Thanks can be enough for us to render him for this mercy? <note place="margin">Pſal. 137.6.</note> 
               <hi>If I forget thee, O Ieruſalem,</hi> and him that brought me hither, <hi>then let my tongue cleave to the roof of my mouth.</hi> The People ſaid it of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> when they were in <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> and we that are returned to <hi>Sion</hi> have reaſon to ſay in much more. <hi>Then if I prefer not Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem in my mirth,</hi> as it follows there; if I take not all occaſions to do it, I were very unthankful. And here my Text leads me to it; 'tis a word in ſeaſon, <note place="margin">Pro. 25.11.</note> 
               <hi>Like apples of Gold in pictures of Silver:</hi> Therefore let us view theſe Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures well, and feed upon theſe Apples; and 'tis not,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153008:7"/>
               <q>—Pictura paſcit inani;</q> but if any thing, Golden Apples will ſatisfie.</p>
            <p>And here we have them in this Text, and upon this occaſion:
<q>Quis dabit ſalutare Iſrael? Who will give ſalvation unto Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, out of Sion? When the Lord, &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This Pſalm begins with <hi>Dixit inſipiens, The fool hath ſaid in his heart, There is no God.</hi> The proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the wicked is the ſeed of Atheiſm; and while Gods own People lay under a Captivity for no leſs then 70. years together, and their enemies, the <hi>Babyloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> carried all before them; no wonder if ſuch fools ſprung up every where, where the ſeed was ſown, ſuch as denied God in their hearts.</p>
            <p>This hath been the old quarrel againſt Heaven: <hi>Crimen illud De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arum Scylla felix,</hi> as <hi>Sencca</hi> ſayes; That wicked men ſhould proſper
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153008:7"/>in the world, and good men be of the ſuffering ſide, is a fault, we think, which Heaven cannot an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. Who would ſerve God upon ſuch hard conditions? <hi>Ergo fruſtra, Then have I cleanſed my heart in vain, Pſal.</hi> 73.13. If I muſt ſerve God for nought, nay, for that which is worſe then no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; if I muſt be perſecuted for my Religion, for my Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, and performing that which was my duty both to God and Man, while the Violators of both are in a better condition; no wonder if we ſee a large field of Atheiſm preſently, and ſuch fools ſpring up in every corner. The Devil waters the ſeed; theſe proſper in the world, ſayes he, preſently, and no body thrives but themſelves; and therefore they conclude from thence, either that there is no God, or, if there be, that he cares not for humane affairs.
<q>Scilicet is ſuper is labor eſt.—</q>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:153008:8"/>They do but laugh at Religion, and the profeſſors of it.</p>
            <p>Hence you may ſee the ſad effects of it, in this Pſalm you may make the Parallel of it your ſelves, (for I deſire not to rub up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſore more then I muſt needs) and obſerve, how our Atheiſts and theirs have jump'd. <hi>Their throat is an open ſepulchre,</hi> Verſe 4. <hi>With their tongues they deceive, the poyſon of Aſps is under their lips.</hi> There's Honey and Gall very near one another: 'tis not <hi>Fel in corde,</hi> that's further off, Poyſon in their hearts; but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their lips; while the Honey is upon them they deceive with their tongues. Then, <hi>Their feet are ſwift to ſhed bloud,</hi> at the next Verſe. No Atheiſt makes any Conſcience of that: they do not fear leſt their Brothers bloud, like <hi>Abels,</hi> ſhould cry to God, while they make God no better then the Image of <hi>Baal,</hi> that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153008:8"/>hear the cry of it. Hence <hi>velo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces pedes,</hi> their feet are very ſwift upon ſuch a deſign, no murther ſhall ſtick with them; nor any other deſtruction neither, though it tend to the ruine and deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of whole Kingdoms. For that's the way they tread in, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felicitas in viis, Deſtruction and unhappineſs is in their wayes, and the way of peace have they not known.</hi> No, that's a way they were never acquainted with; but, like <hi>Jehu,</hi> they drive furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, from one wickedneſs to another; but to look back to the wayes of Peace and Accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, is a crime unpardonable; <hi>For there is no fear of God before their eyes,</hi> in that Verſe: there the fool peeps out of them again; there is no God, and there is no fear of him, 'tis all one; for if there were a God, they muſt fear him whether they would or no.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:153008:9"/>
            <p>And yet they fear their own ſhadows in the mean time: <hi>They were afraid where no fear was,</hi> Verſe 9. Atheiſts are the moſt cowardly men in the world; you know what we owe to their fears and jealouſies. They ſtudy no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but ſelf-preſervation, and fear them that can kill the body onely; but to fear Hell-fire, and him that can caſt them into that for their evil deeds, that's <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riculamentum puerorum,</hi> but a Bugbear to affright Children. Hence they turn <hi>Cannibals</hi> at the 8. Verſe, all ſuch workers of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs, that <hi>They eat up my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as it were bread;</hi> and if they eat the bread that ſhould ſuſtain them,
'tis all one.</p>
            <p>Why then is it a wonder, if in the midſt of ſuch calamities men cry out for a deliverance, and wait for the perſon that brings it? That we have in the Text, and 'tis pardonable if they ſeem to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153008:9"/>grow impatient for it, after ſo many years Captivity. <hi>Quis da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit ſalutare Iſrael? Who ſhall give ſalvation unto Iſrael? &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here then we have,
<list>
                  <item>1. The Captives mourning.</item>
                  <item>2. His Deliverance and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Captives mourning in the firſt words, <hi>Who ſhall give ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation unto Iſrael?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Deliverance and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in the later, <hi>When the Lord turneth the Captivity of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt Part,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Thing to be conſidered is the thing they want or long for, that's Salvation or Deliverance.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The perſon that ſhould bring it or work it for them; and who that ſhould be they cannot tell themſelves, onely <hi>Quis dabit,</hi> they enquire after him, and in what quarter of the world he is to be found; who ſhall give ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:153008:10"/>
            <p n="3">3. Having better bethought themſelves, they will not look abroad for him, but <hi>ex Sion:</hi> Thence he muſt come when all's done, out of <hi>Sion;</hi> not out of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> the place of their Captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but out of <hi>Sion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond Part we have,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The miſery the People lay under, and from which they deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be delivered; that's no leſs then Captivity and abſolute Slavery.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Author of their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, that no other then God himſelf, for Man could not do it; <hi>Cum averterit Dominus, When the Lord turneth the Captivity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The manner how he brings it to paſs, which is very ſtrange and unuſual, he turns it, as if he would turn a River to the Spring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The next thing is the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that are delivered, they his own People, <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153008:10"/>it follows, <hi>Captivitatem plebis ſuae, The captivity of his people.</hi> For which you have</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Peoples Triumph in the laſt place, and that expreſſed in two words, that you may not think 'twas an ordinary triumph in them, <hi>Exultabit &amp; laetabitur, Then ſhall</hi> Jacob <hi>rejoyce, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſhall be glad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt begin with the Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing part, the Deliverance and Triumph ſhall follow after.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who ſhall give ſalvation unto</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael <hi>out of</hi> Sion? Where the</p>
            <p>Firſt thing to be conſidered is the thing they long for, which is Salvation or Deliverance.</p>
            <p>And becauſe Contraries do beſt illuſtrate one another, we will joyn the Captivity with it, and handle them together; the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity with the Salvation, and ſo 'tis But Salvation and Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance out of Captivity. Did I ſay <hi>But?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:153008:11"/>
            <p>Why, can there be any delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance greater then that? Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity is the greateſt croſs that can befall us in the world: for we are carried from our ſelves by it, and put out of our own power. He that is Captive is under the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of another, and ſlavery is the beſt he can look for, for he may kill him if he pleaſe: He hath <hi>poteſtatem vitae &amp; necis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Grot. de jure belli, lib.</hi> 3.</note> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Roman</hi> Law; <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus quòd ſervatus,</hi> ſayes <hi>Donatus;</hi> he may do what he will with him, either kill him, or keep him alive. And the <hi>Babylonian</hi> Law certainly was no better, we have reaſon to think it was worſe, if worſe might be, becauſe they were a leſs-civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized People: And <hi>Jeremy,</hi> that was one of the Children of the captivity, and felt it, did not write his <hi>Lamentations</hi> for nothing; <hi>O vos omnes, qui tranſitis;</hi> ('twould move a ſtone that which he ſayes there, or any that have not hearts
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153008:11"/>of ſtone; and 'twas ſpoken of the People in Captivity, though af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards applied to the ſufferings of Chriſt:) <hi>O all you that paſs by the way, ſee and conſider, if there be any ſorrow like unto mine, Lam.</hi> 1.12. <hi>with which God hath afflicted me in the day of his fierce anger:</hi> 'tis <hi>vindemiavit me</hi> in the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, as if he had trodden them in a Wine-preſs; and we have that word in the 15. Verſe of the Chapter, <hi>He hath trodden the Wine-preſs of the Virgin;</hi> that is, He hath broken and bruiſed her therein. Surely Gods anger was very fierce when it came to that, and the <hi>Babylonians</hi> mercies were very cruel. Do but remember the fiery Furnace in <hi>Daniel,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dan. 6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and the Den of Lions, into which himſelf was caſt; and then you will conceive the Captivity to be, as it deſerves to be conceived, very ſad.</p>
            <p>And 'twas very long and laſting
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153008:12"/>too, for no leſs then 70. years it continued; and they ſaw ſeveral Changes in it, till at laſt God raiſed up the ſpirit of <hi>Cyrus</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver them, as you may read <hi>Ezra</hi> 1.1. And under ſuch a Captivity is it a wonder if the People long for a Redeemer? Of their redemption from the ſlavery of Sin I ſpeak not, by the great Redeemer of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Chriſt Jeſus, of which this Redemption was a Type, and which ought to ſtir up our longing much more, but of our redemption from the ſlavery of Men onely, which is intended as the proper work of this day.</p>
            <p>And ſurely the news of a deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance would be very welcom, though it be but Temporal, to men that are in Captivity, as the <hi>Jews</hi> were here. The <hi>Mournings</hi> of ſuch may be heard far, when but their <hi>Sighs</hi> reach to the ears of God himſelf: <hi>Let the powerful
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153008:12"/>ſighing of the Priſoners come before thee, Pſal.</hi> 79. But their mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is like the mourning of <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dadrimmon, great mourning, Zech.</hi> 12.11. And then 'tis no wonder, I ſay, if the People long for a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance, the next thing in the Text.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Quis dabit ſalutare</hi> Iſrael? <hi>Who ſhall give ſalvation unto</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael? You may turn it into a ſigh if you will, according to another reading of it, <hi>O that the ſalvation were come!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſuch Aſpirations cannot be concealed in hearts that be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with grief: Sorrow will break out at the lips as well as at the eyes of men. — <hi>Ingentes ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,</hi> — They may ſometimes ſilence us, 'tis true, but yet they will be heard ever and anon, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a ſigh in one reading, or in a diſtinct voice in another, 'tis all one; but Deliverance is the thing they would have, every
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:153008:13"/>body underſtands that, <hi>Who ſhall give ſalvation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Ex Sion,</hi> we will put that into it too. The <hi>Jews</hi> looked for their ſalvation out of <hi>Sion,</hi> though they were Captives at <hi>Babylon,</hi> yet their ſalvation they thought muſt come from <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.</hi> They were right, as to their ſpiritual Redemption from ſin, and they had read <hi>Balaam's</hi> Prophecy no doubt, <hi>Orietur ſtella ex Jacob, There ſhall come a ſtar out of Jacob, and a ſceptre ſhall ariſe out of Iſrael, and ſhall ſmite the corners of Moah, and deſtroy all the children of Seth, Num.</hi> 24.17. Therefore out of <hi>Sion</hi> their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer was to come, ſo far they were right.</p>
            <p>Onely they miſtook the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption he was to work for them; and ſo did many others after them, even the Diſciples themſelves, <note place="margin">Luk. 14.21.</note> when they cried, <hi>Nos ſperabamus, But we truſted that it
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:153008:13"/>was he that ſhould have redeemed Iſrael;</hi> that was from their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Captivity, as they imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, bringing a Temporal King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom with him, in the mean time forgetting what the Angel ſaid at his birth, <hi>He ſhall ſave the people from their ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No, their ſins they were not ſo ſenſible of, but of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſufferings by men; and therefore <hi>Ibi digitus,</hi> he that will deliver them from them, is the onely Redeemer they look after. Why, he muſt come from <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> or from the <hi>Medes</hi> rather, pointed at long before he was born for this deliverance, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 44.28. <hi>That ſaith of Cyrus, He is my ſhepherd, and ſhall perform all my pleaſure, ſaying to Jeruſalem, Thou ſhalt be built, and to the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, The foundation ſhall be laid.</hi> Well, if we may be aſſured of that, that we ſhall be delivered, 'tis no matter whence the Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:153008:14"/>comes, <hi>Dummodo conſtat de re,</hi> ſo we may be aſſured of the thing, no matter for perſons, or places either: <hi>Out of Sion,</hi> we will leave that out of the Text, rather then fail of what we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, <hi>Who ſhall give ſalvation unto Iſrael?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have done with the Mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning part, I ſhould now come to the Deliverance and Triumph: But all this concerns the <hi>Jews</hi> Mourning onely; 'tis but <hi>Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentes in plateis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccles. 12.5.</note> in <hi>Eccleſiastes, Man goes to his long home, and the Mourners go about the ſtreets.</hi> We muſt bring them home to our Houſes too, and make a part of this Pomp our ſelves, or we do nothing.</p>
            <p>And if ever any People had cauſe to mourn, this Nation had it too. Let the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity hereafter not be mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, we in <hi>England</hi> have out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done them; in this at leaſt, that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:153008:14"/>the <hi>Jews</hi> were Captives to ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, we to our own Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cic. de Off. l.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Magnum eſt iiſdem uti ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cris, ſepulchra habere communia:</hi> Why, all that is nothing; The ſame Religion and the ſame Graves could not excuſe us, but we were made ſlaves unto them.</p>
            <p>Nay, thoſe that ruled over us for the moſt part were our ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants: <hi>Dominati ſunt ſervi noſtri, <note place="margin">Lam. 5.</note> Servants have ruled over us.</hi> And then, abating that we were not carried abroad, and forced into Exile, though that hath been the caſe with too many of us, and with Him eſpecially who ſhould have ruled over us in the mean time, wherein come we ſhort of the <hi>Jews?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I would not be thought ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious to aggravate our miſeries: Indeed I cannot; and there was never leſs need of an Orators In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention then on this ſubject, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe when we have ſaid all we
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:153008:15"/>can, as the Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> ſaid of <hi>Solomons</hi> Wiſdom, <hi>Half is not told you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I wiſh I had not ſuch a Field to walk in; a Field, not to gather flowers in, but a <hi>Golgotha,</hi> a place of dead mens Skuls, or of Bones; an <hi>Aceldama,</hi> a Field of bloud, in which every ſtep I make, I muſt be over ſhooes in it. <note place="margin">Plin Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r.</note> And how then can I be ſilent? <hi>Utinam eſſet ratio minuendi,</hi> as he ſaid in his Panegyrick, Let ſome body ſhew me the way to leſſen them, for there's no fear of multiplying our miſeries.</p>
            <p>But 'twas an abſolute Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity we were in as well as the <hi>Jews:</hi> Our Lives at the devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of others, and there was not a year paſt but there muſt be ſome new Rubricks in our Calendar; they ſpeak of Red-letter-men, they have made the Calendar red indeed with the bloud of perſons of all ranks, of Citizens, of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:153008:15"/>Gentlemen, of Clergy-men, of Nobles; ſhall I ſay of a King too? <hi>O tell it not in Gath, nor pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh it in the ſtreets of Askelon.</hi> Let Hiſtories paſs it over in ſilence, let the Annals of that year be buried in oblivion, let Forty eight be expunged out of our account, and the Thirtieth of <hi>January</hi> out of the Calendar of <hi>England;</hi> 'tis a day to be remembred with hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, a day of darkneſs and black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for ever. This Rhetorick is to be pardoned me,
<q>
                  <l>— Ignoſcite, ſi quid</l>
                  <l>Intumuit pietas, <note place="margin">Claudian.</note> —</l>
               </q> He is a fool that is not eloquent upon this ſubject, and a juſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation forces it from me. Yet I pardon the Contrivers of it, and ſo may others too, for I my ſelf was not innocent: If I had been, and you that hear me, that glorious Prince could not
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:153008:16"/>have ſuffered: <hi>But the Crown is fallen from our heads, and woe unto us becauſe we have ſinned,</hi> as the Prophet makes the <hi>Lamentation, chap.</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 16. I remember 'twas the obſervation of Mr. <hi>Vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell,</hi> one that ſuffered for the King, <hi>That there were ſome people in the world, who once a year ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed men to the Devils, like thoſe who offered their children to Molech.</hi> I did not think they had lived in this Iſland, till we ſaw thoſe Anniverſaries kept here.</p>
            <p>But theſe are the effects of a Captivity, where mens lives are at the devotion of others: And then that their Eſtates were ſo 'tis no wonder: The other was the Anniverſary, this the Daily, Sacrifice of theſe <hi>Jews;</hi> we were <hi>killed all the day long</hi> in this ſenſe, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſal. 44.2.</note> in our Livelyhoods and our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates: And it had been more mercy to ſome, that wanted bread in the mean time, if they
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:153008:16"/>had been killed out-right.</p>
            <p>But Captive men muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with any thing, nay, with nothing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>— Quod captis ſat eſt,—vivamus.</hi> For the Conquerors told us, All was their own. And ſo they did not bluſh to tell God too, their <hi>Levites</hi> eſpecially, when they thanked him for ſuffering them to ſit under their own Vines, and their Fig-trees; when alas! all this while they were other mens. <hi>Alas, Maſter, it was borrowed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings 6.5.</note> I will not ſay, it was ſtollen; while they have eaten other mens bread, and could not afford us the crums that fell from their Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, not by their good wills, a Tenth part inſtead of a Fifth. I am ſorry for their uncharitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>But what was become of their Religion in the mean time? Why that was gone with the reſt, they have mixed—<hi>ſacra profanis,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:153008:17"/>and wrapped up all together, and are gone with it. <note place="margin">Joh. 20.2.</note> 
               <hi>They have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away my Lord, and I know not where they have laid him, Mary</hi> ſaid weeping: We have no cauſe to laugh, when we tell you they had taken away his Service, his Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, his Rites, and the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church, &amp; the Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance thereof, and we know not where they have laid them too; ſurely 'twill be hard to find them again in ſuch a Confuſion as they have made; but God, we truſt, will gather them out of the duſt and rubbiſh of the Temple, and reſtore them to their ancient ſplendor, that we may worſhip God in the Beauty of Holineſs again.</p>
            <p>In the mean time no man will blame us, if while we ſate by the waters of <hi>Babylon,</hi> during the time of our Captivity, we have been heard to ſigh ſometimes, and to aske after a Deliverance. <hi>Nemo felicitatis ſuae obliviſcitur,</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:153008:17"/>as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſayes, We cannot for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get our former happineſs. And this hath been our imployment for want of a better, <note place="margin">Luk. 7.32.</note> like <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſitting in the Market-place,</hi> becauſe no man hath hired us. Who will give ſalvation? God help us, we have had too much leaſure to enquire and to aske af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it, <hi>Quis dabit,</hi> whence our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance ſhould come, whether from the Eaſt, or from the Weſt, from the North, or from the South; for we had our Times to hope for it from all Quarters: And then as one failed, by and by we were ready to ſay as <hi>Mordecai</hi> did to <hi>Heſter,
<note place="margin">Heſt 4.14.</note> Deliverance ſhall come another way.</hi> But one way or other we had to expect it ſtill, and <hi>Quis dabit</hi> was the onely ſong of <hi>Sion</hi> then, inſtead of all other Anthems of the Church, <hi>Who ſhall give ſalvation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed the <hi>Jews</hi> might have taught us not to expect it from
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:153008:18"/>
               <hi>Babylon,</hi> though we thought ſometimes it might come from thence.
<note place="margin">Saluſt.</note> 
               <hi>Aut in mederi potes, aut omittenda eſt cura omnibus,</hi> as 'twas ſaid of <hi>Caeſar</hi> in the Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and that either a Catholick or a Chriſtian King, or both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, would do it, and help him who was the true Defender of the Faith.</p>
            <p>But this was an Error in us; and though the <hi>Iews</hi> had it not there, yet <hi>ex Sion,</hi> out of <hi>Sion</hi> was our deliverance to come. God would not have us to be behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the King of <hi>Sodom,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 14.23.</note> or to any forreign State, to bring home <hi>Abraham,</hi> or to ſay, I have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched the People: But our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance muſt come out of <hi>Sion;</hi> thoſe of our own Religion, of our own Nation, muſt do it. And, God be thanked, they did; we know not how dear it might have coſt us had it been otherwiſe. 'Tis not good to lay the Cloth to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:153008:18"/>ſtrangers; it may be when they had eaten our Meat, the Diſhes would not have ſufficed them. But <hi>Sion</hi> muſt deliver it ſelf, and free us from theſe Oppreſſions; elſe the Remedy might have been as bad as the Diſeaſe, and the Patient have ſuffered by them both.</p>
            <p>It was Gods infinite mercy this, and let him onely have the glory of it, that we fell into the hands of ſuch Phyſicians that were tender of us, and have wrought this Cure upon a ſick State without any Phlebotomies at all. We had been uſed ſo much to bloud-letting before, that they knew 'twould do us no good; and therefore it muſt be <hi>ſine ſanguine,</hi> without bloud now, when our Sacrifices are reſtored, though <hi>Pilate</hi> mixed bloud with them when the War began. We owe this under God to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of a wiſe General, whoſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:153008:19"/>memory ſhall be glorious for it, and who conquer'd without fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: It was <hi>vidi, vici,</hi> a maiden Victory he obtained, and his Eyes onely were triumphant. But this bleſſing we have <hi>ex Sion,</hi> that our deliverance came out of <hi>Sion;</hi> for though it were a Northern Army, they had none of the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Ice in them; but moſt, if not all, of them were our own Countrey-men and Friends.</p>
            <p>I have ſaid enough of the firſt part of the Text, and kept you too long in mourning. And yet if you conſider how long we have kept our ſelves in it, and that 'tis but proportionable to that, you will pardon me. 'Twas a long Captivity, almoſt the third part of the <hi>Babylonian:</hi> And how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are delivered from the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of the Body, while they waited for this deliverance of the Nation? Our Fathers and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren are gone moſt of them while
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:153008:19"/>they expected it, like thoſe <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> that dyed in the Wilderneſs, <note place="margin">Num. 14.23.</note> and could never get further then the firſt part of this Text, <hi>Who ſhall give ſalvation unto Iſrael out of Sion?</hi> 'Tis Gods infinite mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to me, which I muſt ever mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie, that I live to preach upon the ſecond, and to have a ſhare in this Triumph.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>When the Lerd turned the Captivity of his People, &amp;c.</hi> And my diſcourſe now ſhall be moſt at home, the Argument of a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance being more pleaſing. And here,</p>
            <p n="1">1. God ſtands in the gap, the Author of this deliverance, <hi>Cum averterit Dominus, When the Lord turneth the captivity.</hi> The <hi>Iews</hi> might have ſaid, <hi>Cyrus</hi> turned it, <note place="margin">2 Chron. 26.</note> that ſent them back, or <hi>Darius,</hi> or <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> abroad; or elſe <hi>Ezra</hi> turned it, or <hi>Nehemias,</hi> or <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> at home: All theſe contributed much toward it, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:153008:20"/>yet 'tis, <hi>Cum averterit Dominus, When the Lord turneth the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis not good to admire In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments when the Workman himſelf is in place; as if a man ſhould commend his Club, and take no notice of <hi>Hercules:</hi> and Men are but the Inſtruments of God, as a ſword in the hand of a Giant. Gods ſcourges wicked men are, as 'twas ſaid of <hi>Tamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane,</hi> that he was <hi>Flagellum Dei;</hi> they may kill or ſave, be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Inſtruments of our delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or curſed Inſtruments of our deſtruction. But the Hand and the Contrivance is Gods. Therefore let all fleſh be ſilent, not ſo much as named, in a Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance eſpecially. But let God onely have the glory of it, for he onely hath done it; no body elſe could. Men cannot work Miracles; <note place="margin">Exo. 8.19.</note> but the Magicians ſaid it was <hi>Digitus Dei,</hi> when it came
<pb facs="tcp:153008:20"/>to that: This is the Finger of God, and therefore let not the Arme of Fleſh interpoſe in it.</p>
            <p>Gods hand is in our ordinary deliverances, which he works for us every day; and 'tis an iſſue of his Providence that we ſleep in ſafety every night. <hi>There is no Evil in the city which God hath not done,</hi> and therefore no Good much more. But there be ſome deliverances which are written at length, and not in Figures, as they uſe to ſay, that is, they are legible to every eye, even a blind man may ſee them. Here Gods finger comes in too; like <hi>Apelles</hi> upon the Table, no body could do it but himſelf, and therefore no body would touch the Pencil after him: Or like <hi>Hercules,</hi> we might know he had been there by the print of his foot. So God leaves the print of his hand and his finger behind him in ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances, which no Mortal dares
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:153008:21"/>to counterfeit; for if he ſhould, every body would ſee the Forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and he deſerved to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed.</p>
            <p>And ſuch a Deliverance was ours: the Characters of it are ſo plain and diſtinct, that are cannot poſſibly miſtake. When God wrote <hi>Mene Tekel</hi> upon the wall of the Kings Palace, while he ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſed in the Veſſels of the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary, <note place="margin">Dan. 5.5, 6.</note> the Text ſayes, <hi>The King ſaw part of the hand that wrote it, and his countenance was changed, and his knees ſmote one againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> Here was Gods hand viſible in a judgment, and I pray take notice, 'twas for Sacrilege. And did we think that any ſin when time was? if we did, methinks we ſhould have been afraid of the Hand too. But his hand is as vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible in ſome mercies as in ſome judgments; when 'tis as it were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and no hand can do it but his: Not all the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:153008:21"/>in the world; they his juſt their Art produce Frogs, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> truck in ordinary wares like ſo many <hi>Hocus-Pocus's;</hi> but when it comes to a deliverance, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally a extraordinary one, ſuch as a dividing the Sea, and carrying the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> thorough it; then <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> his hand onely muſt do it, by Gods immediate power and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand: Then 'tis, <note place="margin">Ex. 14.16.</note> 
               <hi>Extende ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num tuam, Stretch out thy hand ever the ſea, and divide it.</hi> And leſt any man ſhould think <hi>Moſes</hi> had done it by his own hand, and not Gods, therefore <hi>David</hi> aſcribes it to God onely, and not to <hi>Moſes, Pſal.</hi> 136.12. <hi>In manu potenti, &amp; brachio excelſo,</hi> he brought out <hi>Iſrael</hi> from among them. He that did all the reſt there, <hi>with a mighty hand and ſtretched out arm.</hi> Alas! <hi>Moſes</hi> his hands were not ſo you know, they grew heavy, and were fain to be ſtayed up, <note place="margin">Ex. 17.12.</note> not long after <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Hur</hi> did it;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:153008:22"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> they were not mighty o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> themſelves, no more were his arms neither. And though they ſay Kings have long arms, and may reach far; yet 'tis but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their own ſphere, when all's done they can reach no further, but they have bones and fleſh in them as well as other mens. 'Tis God onely that can do things <hi>brachio excelſo, with a ſtretched-out arme,</hi> and no body elſe.</p>
            <p>And whether Gods arme were not ſtretched out in our Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance I need not aske you. 'Tis true, there was no ſuch apparent Miracle in it, as the dividing the Sea, or cutting the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Ocean in ſunder, to bring over the King on dry land: No, that was need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs in his caſe, when he had ſo many Ships ready to convey him. And God doth not work Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles when ordinary remedies are at hand, though that was Miracle enough, even the ſudden ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:153008:22"/>of the Sea men to his juſt power. It might be ſaid of him in a qualified ſenſe, which the People ſaid of our Saviour when he aſſwaged the Tempeſt, <hi>What manner of man is this, whom both the wind and the ſeas obey?</hi> For there had been a Tempeſt as well at Sea as at Land. They uſe to ſay, <hi>If it be foul weather upon the Land, 'tis worſe at Sea:</hi> Yet I know not how the Sea was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed, and there was a Calm upon the ſudden, and all conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the completing the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle here.</p>
            <p>But upon the Land how many Miracles have been wrought? Firſt, that more then 30. Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, as they were once at <hi>Athens,</hi> ſhould upon the ſudden, when they thought their Power ſecured, and themſelves ſcant Mortals, be wrought out by one, when that one ſhould be arreſted by death in the midſt of Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:153008:23"/>and he had as much need of a Remembrancer as the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> had in theirs, That he was a Man, when the Son of that Man, or Monſter rather, ſhould ſo eaſily quit his power to them that could not keep it, but were forced to call in the old Riders again; for the Commonwealth, as it muſt be called, was tyred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and yet they muſt again bow down their backs to them.</p>
            <p>Well, the wheel of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence was now going, and every Change ſeemed a Deliverance to us: It was ſo as to the event; for as if they had been playing a game at Cheſs, while their deſign was to check him, they did but take up one another to make room for the King.</p>
            <p>But we for the preſent had lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle eaſe by it; we did but change for the worſe ſtill. The old flies were leſs to be dreaded, <hi>quoniam hipleni,</hi> as the Horſe ſaid in the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:153008:23"/>Fable, while the new ones came with ſharper Appetites upon us. Onely ſome comfort there was in the very Change. <note place="margin">Mal. 3.6.</note> We are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to it in our ſelves, and all that is about us: Onely God can ſay, <hi>Ego non mutor, I am not chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged:</hi> We are, therefore we love it, and make a vertue of it, and are glad of Changes every hour. 'Tis ſtrange none ſhould be for the better, that among ſo many Caſts there ſhould be none good. We were uſed indeed as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour was, <note place="margin">Luke 23.</note> ſent from <hi>Annas</hi> to <hi>Caiphas,</hi> from <hi>Caiphas</hi> to <hi>Pilate,</hi> from <hi>Pilate</hi> to <hi>Herod,</hi> and then back again to <hi>Pilate;</hi> but where was Juſtice all this while? for the Judges we ſee. Indeed we had too much of that ſometimes, and their very mercies were cruel-But here was no Deliverance, but from one Tormentor to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, not a good caſt yet. Why, all were good, and they did Gods
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:153008:24"/>work, and the Kings, when they were moſt againſt him.</p>
            <p>We are now in this laſt year of Providences, ſo many and ſo great, that it may be much more juſtly called <hi>Annus mirabilis</hi> then that of 88. was. Providences abroad in the general peace of Chriſtendom, that <hi>Janus</hi> his Temple might have been ſhut up again; which I take to be not the leaſt of Gods Providences to us, for that peace conduced to ours: And Providences at home, even to a Miracle, that the Hills ſhould be brought low, thoſe Mountains of proud and ſelf-intereſted men which were thought inſuperable, that the Vallies ſhould be exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the way laid even, as it were, <note place="margin">Luke 3.5.</note> and <hi>prepared for him,</hi> as <hi>Iohn the Baptiſt</hi> ſaid of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our at his coming, and all rubs out of it, that all fleſh might ſee the ſalvation of God, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance of this Nation. For it
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:153008:24"/>is Salvation, though but Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, that which was chiefly inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in this Text, and a delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance out of Captivity, <hi>Who ſhall give ſalvation unto Iſrael?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now you are all ready to anſwer, <hi>Cum averterit Dominus,</hi> it is Gods ſalvation, and it is he onely that hath given it, and therefore we give him onely the glory of it; not unto us, nor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him we moſt admire in it, as his Inſtrument, but unto him. And let it be entred into our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, and made the Title-page of the Hiſtory of our Times, <hi>Hoc fecit Dominus,
<note place="margin">Mat. 21.42.</note> This hath God done, and it is marvellous in our eyes.</hi> And as our Saviour ſaid of the Woman that anointed his feet, <hi>Whereſoever this Goſpel ſhall be read,</hi> for it is good Tidings too, <hi>there ſhall this alſo be told;</hi> not which ſhe, but he himſelf hath done for us. His Doing is much more conſpicuous if we conſider,</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:153008:25"/>
            <p n="2">2. The Manner of it in the next circumſtance of the Text, <hi>Cum averterit, When he Turns the captivity.</hi> The Turning of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Captivity was very ſtrange and very ſudden; for we find it in the laſt of the <hi>Chronicles,</hi> after he had deſcribed the deſtruction of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and the Peoples car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying away, immediately at the next Verſe, <hi>Now the Lord ſtirred up the ſpirit of Cyrus, that he made a Proclamation, and ſaid, Who is there among you of his people, the Lord his God be with him, and let him go up to Ieruſalem,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.22. This was all the prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration toward it, God ſtirred up the heart of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> and the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity was turned upon the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</p>
            <p>And ſo was ours too; God ſtirred up the hearts of ſome worthy Perſons, and after ſome Turns among our Oppreſſors, that went off the ſtage as <hi>Praelu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium's</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:153008:25"/>to it, our Captivity was turned too. <note place="margin">Saluſt.</note> 
               <hi>Et tandem vicit for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuna Reipublicae,</hi> as the Hiſtorian ſaid.</p>
            <p>'Twas turned as a River to the Spring-head,
<q>— Xanthe retro propera, —</q> Rivers do not uſe to do ſo, but they run to the Sea. And ſo did our Rivers, the current of the Nation was ſo, after ſuch a tract of time, the courſe of the ſtream was almoſt grown naturall, into the Sea, or into a Gulph rather, like <hi>Scylla</hi> and <hi>Charybdis,</hi> that ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, and devoured every thing.</p>
            <p>Here then was the Miracle, that God turned the ſtream upon it ſelf, one Army upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the people upon thoſe that had miſ-led them, they came down like a Torrent, 'twas not ſafe for any body to ſtand in their way. 'Twas anſwerable to what the people prayed for, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.5. <hi>Turn our Captivity, O Lord, as
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:153008:26"/>the Rivers in the South.</hi> What was the naturall courſe of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers in the South, I know not. But I know the Rivers in the North had a ſtrange turn at this time, when a man might ſee the whole ſtream of the Nation run a contrary way upon the ſuddain, to what they had been uſed.</p>
            <p>This is that, that makes us yet think we are but in a Dream, we cannot think we are awaked, to ſee ſuch a turn as this is, but that we Dream of happineſſe one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And yet we are awaked, God be thanked for it. And the Lord hath turned our Captivity.</p>
            <p>Ours, thats the Captivity</p>
            <p n="3">3. Of his people. We do not deſerve that title, whatever the <hi>Iews</hi> did.
<note place="margin">Pſ. St. 12.</note> 
               <hi>But my people would not hear my voice, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>would not obey me.</hi> God complaines of them; And certainly we have not been very forward to hear it, elſe we had not been puniſhed as they were.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:153008:26"/>
            <p>But whatever their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were, you ſee, God owns them for his people ſtill. And God uſeth to puniſh his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple more ſeverely, then he doth others: Becauſe their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence is more unpardonable, as a Rebellious Childs is then a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants. <hi>Et tu Fili,</hi> ſuch an ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude muſt needs go near the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>To whom much is given, <note place="margin">Lu. 12.48.</note> of him much ſhall be required,</hi> and therefore if he ſmart for it, he muſt thank himſelf. And yet 'tis <hi>quos diligo,</hi> ſtill he loves them whom he chaſtiſeth, and he will not renounce them for his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren for all that.</p>
            <p>And yet ſome men have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to make us believe, That thoſe that were under the Rod were none of his Children, and that Temporal Proſperity was the onely mark of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour. This is one of the new Doctrines indeed, but the old was
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:153008:27"/>quite contrary: And yet how of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten have we been told to our Heads, as we uſe to ſay, That our Cauſe was not good becauſe the iſſue was not ſucceſsful? In the mean time I have often wondred at their Foreheads, that would tye Goodneſs and Succeſs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes together; which if it were true, muſt make Chriſtians to be worſe then Turks.</p>
            <p>Well, howſoever I may be out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced, I ſhall never fall into this Hereſie, as long as I ſee <hi>Plebis ſuae</hi> in the Text, and Gods own Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in a Captivity too. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that muſt comfort us in the remembrance of our ſufferings; and now that we are out of them, oblige us to that which this Text calls for in the laſt place,</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Peoples Triumph and Thankfulneſs, <hi>Exultabit Iacob &amp; laetabitur Iſrael, Then ſhall Iacob re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, and Iſrael ſhall be glad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then it ſeems 'tis a Duty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:153008:27"/>upon us to give Thanks for a Deliverance. We ſay, He can do little, that cannot ſay, I thank you: And that Courteſie that is not worth Thanks, is worth nothing. And yet how many tongue-tyed men are there in the world, that cannot bring out ſuch a word? when it comes to that, they have an impediment in their ſpeech, and yet they can ſpeak any thing elſe very plain. <hi>Moleſtum hoc verbum, Rogo, Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi> ſayes: Some men do not love to aske a good turn, and others love as little to acknowledge it; but let the benefit lye in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, and we'l take it; as for <hi>Rogo</hi> or <hi>Gratias ago,</hi> at both ends of it, we think 'tis none of our buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; eſpecially to ſay, I thank you; there be very few that can pronounce it.</p>
            <p>But to ſay, I thank God, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks no body ſhould be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of that, <hi>Who gives liberally,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:153008:28"/>and upbraids not, James</hi> 1.5. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, He doth it ſimply without any reaches in it: They be not <hi>Munera in hamo,</hi> as mens gifts oftentimes uſe to be. And then he doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach us with them neither, nor caſt them in our diſh when the meat is eaten: And therefore we ſhould be ſure to thank him, and to ſay grace before we riſe from the Table; yet we forget it I know not how. As among the Lepers in the Goſpel, <hi>Ubi ſunt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vem?</hi> ſcarce one in ten that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns to give thanks.</p>
            <p>But for Deliverances, ſuch bleſſings as theſe, that are not ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in to us once or twice a day, as our meat is, but once or twice it may be in our whole lives, eſpecially ſuch a Deliverance as this, there is not onely Thanks, but Joy and Exultation due to it: as the Prophet <hi>Zachary</hi> ſayes, <hi>Exulta filia Sion, <note place="margin">Zach. 9.9.</note> Rejoyce greatly,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:153008:28"/>O daughter of Sion, ſhout, O daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Jeruſalem: Behold thy King comes.</hi> 'Twas ſpoken indeed of the King of Kings, and their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual deliverance from their ſins; but, <hi>Ecce, rex tuus venit, Behold, thy King comes,</hi> eſpecially com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as he doth, after ſuch an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terregnum</hi> as we have had, doth deſerve an Exultation from us too.</p>
            <p>And to give the People their due, they have expreſſed it: I think no King was ever received with the like; ſo many re-itera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Triumphs; when they had done they begun again,
<q>— Nec dum finitus, —</q> A man would think they would never have done; ſo loud in their Acclamations, ſo prodigal of their wood in their Bonfires, as if now that the King is come near them, they ſhould never need any fire again, and his Sun would warm them ſtill.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:153008:29"/>
            <p>This was not to be blamed in them, for we have a Triumph warranted in the Text; not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>exultabit,</hi> but <hi>laetabitur;</hi> when one is done t'other ſhall begin, like one Bonfire after another; <hi>Then ſhall Jacob rejoyce, and Iſrael ſhall be glad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And 'tis not onely <hi>Jacob,</hi> but <hi>Iſrael;</hi> leſt any ſhould make ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes, all muſt appear at this So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity. And ſome; it may be, did excuſe it at the firſt Triumph with their Buying of Farms, or Yokes of Oxen, or the like, ſome pretences they had, as many as were over-wary or under-willing, that is, not ſo well-affected as they ſhould be. Why, theſe came in at the ſecond or third Courſe, and there was a kind of <hi>Coge introire</hi> at laſt, they were in a manner compelled to come in, becauſe they durſt not ſtay with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out. But now all joyn in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing; I hope 'tis hearty, and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:153008:29"/>not onely from the Teeth out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: However it comes with a <hi>Nemine contradicente,</hi> No man doth, or no man dares, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict it.</p>
            <p>Why any body ſhould I know not, unleſs they take it ill to be happy, to be freed out of ſlave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to ſee Peace eſtabliſhed, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and the Worſhip of God reſtored. If this be a wrong to them,
<q>—Pol me Occidiſtis Amici—</q> The mad man was wronged, when he was reſtored to his Wits again. But I will not ſuppoſe any body in that condition, though there have been diſtempers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us heretofore, I hope we are all come to our ſelves now, and that we joyn heartily in this Triumph.</p>
            <p>And yet ſome <hi>Elder</hi> Brothers are apt to find fault, and to repine at the Muſick and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Dancing, to aske, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Journey, <hi>If</hi> and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:153008:30"/>as he did, as if 'twere too much or too light for ſuch an occaſion. I would not be thought to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance any Exceſs, or to juſtifie all mens extravagancies at ſuch a time; but do rather reprove them: And when I have done that, I muſt tell you again, as the Father did him in that Parable, <hi>It is meet that we ſhould make mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and rejoyce:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iu. 15.32.</note> for not this thy Brother, but thouſands of thy Brethren were civilly dead, that is, ruined and undone, and now they are alive again, they were loſt and they are found. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſome Exultation may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, if it be one friske it may be excuſed, the Occaſion is not ordinary: <hi>Exultabit Jacob, Jacob ſhal rejoyce greatly,</hi> as the daughter of <hi>Sion</hi> was bid to do before, as they would leap out of their skins, no moderate joy muſt ſerve the turn.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Moderation cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:153008:30"/>for by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> after a re-ite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated joy, as 'tis here, <hi>Again I ſay, <note place="margin">Phil. 4.5.</note> Rejoyce, but let your Moderation be known to all men.</hi> The word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and 'tis rendred <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtia;</hi> and both are needful at this time, a Yielding and a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, now we may ſeem to have the advantage of our Enemies. The leſs there was of it on their ſide when time was, let there be the more of it on ours now; and we muſt not <hi>inſult,</hi> though we may <hi>exult,</hi> for this Deliverance. But let your Moderation be known, 'tis neceſſary for the heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our Breaches, and not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God, but the King, calls upon us for it.</p>
            <p>This is but an Expreſſion of our Thankfulneſs to God; and yet the beſt expreſſion of that, when we have ſaid all we can, is our Obedience. No doubt we have all of us promiſed much,
<note place="margin">Gen. 28.20.</note> as <hi>Iacob</hi> did in his Journey, <hi>If God
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:153008:31"/>will be with me,</hi> if he will but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver us out of this Bondage, then the Lord ſhall be our God. Theſe were our <hi>Tabulae votivae,</hi> ſuch Vows we have made, or at leaſt ſhould have made, every one of us; let us be careful to perform them, and expreſs our thankfulneſs that way. Thoſe be the beſt Trophies we can ſet up, in the Reformation of our Lives; as old <hi>Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> ſaid in his Song, and 'twas a Song of Triumph too,
<note place="margin">Luk. 1.74.</note> 
               <hi>Ut libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti ſerviamus, That we being deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered out of the hands of our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, might ſerve him without fear, in holineſs and righteouſneſs before him all the dayes of our life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis a great happineſs to ſerve God without fear; we have not done ſo for many years together: but as Chriſt came to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, ſo did we to him, the doors being ſhut.
<q>— Et aperto vivere voto, —</q>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:153008:31"/>Every body could not do it; not that they were aſhamed of their Petitions, for they were ſuch as were allowed by Authority, but for fear of their Enemies. And now that this fear is removed, let the Service, I pray you, be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed with more Reverence, with Reverence and Fear ſtill, of God though not of Men. But let's remember the Service, the Service of the Church, not to neglect that, as formerly we have done; and the Service of God eſpecially, that we pay him that Obedience in our Lives which is due to him.</p>
            <p>That the World may not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn us of unthankfulneſs, that it be not ſaid of us as it was of his own People, <note place="margin">Pſal. 78.</note> 
               <hi>Yet for all this they ſinned more againſt him:</hi> 'tis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated twice in that Pſalm, and one ſin of unthankfulneſs is too many.</p>
            <p>But I will not ſuſpect it in a
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:153008:32"/>People ſo obliged as we are: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo delivered, as it is our duty, ſo I doubt not but it ſhall be our buſineſs to ſerve him, even to ſerve him all the dayes of our Lives.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now to God the Father, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:153008:32"/>
            <head>A Sermon preached in the Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dral Church of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> on <hi>Jan. 30. 1661.</hi> being the Anniverſary of the Death of the late King <hi>Charles I.</hi> of glorious memory.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>LAMENT. 4.20.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>The breath of our noſtrils, the Anointed of the Lord was taken in their nets, of whom we ſaid, Under his ſhadow we ſhall live among the heathen.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Book is a Book of <hi>Lamentations,</hi> and ſo is this Day; a Day, wherein to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the loſs of a King; a dumb man would ſpeak, as one did in <hi>Herodotus</hi> to ſave a Kings life. But this Book is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Jeremy's Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations,</hi> the Prophet wrote it in tears, ſo 'tis ſaid in the Vulgar
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:153008:33"/>Tranſlation, <hi>Sedit Jeremias flens &amp; planxit, Jeremy wept and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented when he wrote it:</hi> And well he might, for the occaſion of it was very ſad, even the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> the People were carried to <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the City and Temple deſtroyed; and among the ſpoils there was <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus oris noſtri,</hi> even he that was <hi>The breath of their noſtrils, the Anointed of the Lord.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if the Prophet breath out no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Lamentations and Sighs upon ſuch an occaſion, 'tis no wonder.</p>
            <p>We are indeed this day upon the like ſubject, a day of Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations it is: Let the Prieſt weep between the Porch and the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, and ſo let the People too; for when the <hi>breath of our noſtrils</hi> is gone, the People and Prieſts are both alike, no better then dead trunks every one of us.</p>
            <p>Did I ſay, A Day of Lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions?
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:153008:33"/>Indeed it ſhould not be called a Day, wherein the Sun ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhined. 'Tis ſaid, <hi>There was darkneſs over all the Land untill the ninth hour,</hi> when they cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Chriſt. A man might ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it ſo over this Land of ours, when they murthered the King, and that they came with Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorns and Torches, as they did to apprehend Chriſt, though 'twere at high Noon: For ſure the Sun would not own the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor ſee the murther of Gods Anointed, and therefore let it not be numbred amongſt the dayes any longer. But
<q>— Mira cano, ſol occubuit. —</q> 'Tis a ſad ſtory to remember, the Sun ſate at high Noon. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay,
<q>— Nox nulla ſequuta eſt,</q> as 'twas ſaid of the death of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prince; for after the death of this, there was a continued night amongſt us, no day-light
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:153008:34"/>for ſo many years together; till at laſt the Sun returned, the ſame Sun or a brighter, his Fathers own <hi>Son</hi> it was, and now, God be thanked for it, 'tis day-light again with us.</p>
            <p>But for the day of the Kings death, I would have it wiped out of the Calendar, as there is a day put into the Calendar ſometimes in <hi>February, Dies intercalaris</hi> 'tis called; ſo I would have the Thirtieth of <hi>January</hi> put out, for it will be a reproach to us,
<q>— Titulum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> effeminat anni.</q> 'Tis pity it ſhould be remembred, but that the wiſdom of our Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours will have it ſo, let it be a day of blackneſs and darkneſs for ever.</p>
            <p>And yet we remember the deaths of other Martyrs, the dayes of their deaths are in the Martyrologies of the Church in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of their Birth-dayes, in which they were born to Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality;
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:153008:34"/>and therefore the death of this bleſſed Saint and Martyr deſerves to be remembred too: To be remembred for thoſe Princely Vertues that ſhined in him that day, more then in any other of his life. <hi>How glorious was the King of Iſrael this day? Micah</hi> ſaid it of <hi>David</hi> in a ſcoff, but 'twas true in earneſt: among the many ſcoffs that were put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that glorious Saint, this might be one too; but 'twas a ſad truth nevertheleſs. How glorious was he in his Meekneſs, in his Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, in his Magnanimity, in his Charity, in his Contempt of the world, and all the Glory of it? For he had more Tentations to love it then all his Subjects be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, and therefore how glorious was he in the deſpiſing of it? how glorious was the King of <hi>England</hi> this day? as 'twas ſaid of the Proto-Martyr St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> ſo it might be ſaid of this Royal Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:153008:35"/>too, <hi>All that ſate in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil ſaw his face as it had been the face of an Angel.</hi> But that their eyes were holden that they could not know him, as 'twas ſaid of Chriſt, <hi>Certainly they could not have condemned him. But I ſay unto you, That even Solomon in all his glory was not clothed like one of Theſe;</hi> not like an <hi>ordinary</hi> flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and therefore not like <hi>this flower, This Lilly of the Vallies, this Lilly among Thorns,</hi> as
'tis ſaid of Chriſt there. And certainly if any Lilly beſides Chriſt were planted ſo, this was he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Among the Thorns indeed, that pricked him, and did him all the injuries they could. <hi>Like the Roſe in Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,</hi> as 'tis in that Verſe, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.1. (there are Prickles enough too) <hi>and the Lilly of the vallies.</hi> Never any Lilly ſtood <hi>lower</hi> in the Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, and was clothed with more humility, and therefore the more glorious in that reſpect; and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:153008:35"/>therefore the more fit to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of this day. 'Tis <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> in his <hi>glory, in all his glory;</hi> moſt <hi>richly</hi> apparelled he was, if the <hi>inward</hi> Clothing of the Mind be of any value.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Kings Daughter is all glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious within:</hi> and ſo was the King himſelf, a true Son of that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Spouſe of Chriſt. And therefore He was cloathed like her, <hi>glorious within,</hi> howſoever the wrought Gold in His outward cloathing was taken from Him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Et hinc lachrymae,</hi> here the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation begins. When once they begin to <hi>unking</hi> Him, and to take His Purple, and His Royal Authority from Him, 'twas no hard matter to prophecy what would be the end of the Tragedy. Dead men they ſay have no Teeth, or cannot Bite: and though they had Him ſafe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in their Nets, yet they did not think him ſo, nor themſelves
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:153008:36"/>neither, till He was paſt Biting; The <hi>Chaldeans</hi> were ſatisfied with leſſe Barbarity then this: and yet here's matter enough for a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, though it were but <hi>Captus in Laqueis,</hi> and there be no <hi>Murther</hi> of a King mentioned, <hi>The breath of our noſtrils, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed of the Lord was taken in their Nets, of whom we ſaid, Under his ſhadow, we ſhall live among the Heathen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this Text then we have the Prophets Lamentation, for the ſad condition of a King. And yet, who this King was, Interpreters agree not, whether it were <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah,</hi> or <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> or whether it were <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, He that was the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords. But a King it was, for here we have all the Characters of Him, <hi>ſpiritus Or is noſtri,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtus Domini,</hi> and <hi>In umbra tua vivemus, the breath of our no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils, the Anointed of the Lord, and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:153008:36"/>under his ſhadow we ſhall live a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Heathen;</hi> of whom but a King, can this be ſaid? It mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not what King, for even the worſt of Kings is ſacred, and the loſſe of Him to be lamented. Suppoſe Him to be <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> and He was none of the beſt; as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Chronology, and the reſt of the matter of this Book ſeems to point at Him. But if it were <hi>Joſiah,</hi> as St. <hi>Jerome</hi> and the Hebrew Interpreters think, or if it were <hi>Chriſt</hi> as moſt Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters ſay, what Mourning could be ſufficient? <hi>Mary</hi> ſtood by the Sepulchre weeping: and well ſhe might, for ſuch a loſſe. But we will not reſtrain it to any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, becauſe 'tis proper enough to all, and we may apply it to one whom the Prophet never Dream't of, even <hi>ſpiritus Oris no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri,</hi> He that was <hi>the breath of our noſtrils,</hi> Ours of this Nation, who breathed by him, and dyed with him.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:153008:37"/>
            <p>Firſt then we will obſerve the Characters of him, as they are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven here in the Text, that you may learne to eſteem of him, as he deſerved.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the calamity that befell him, that you may lament the loſſe of him.</p>
            <p>The Characters of him are three.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Spiritus Oris noſtri, he was the breath of our noſtrils,</hi> and thats an endearing expreſſion of him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Chriſtus Domini,</hi> that's a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred expreſſion of him, he was the Anointed of the Lord.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>In umbra tua vivemus,</hi> that will make us know the benefit we had by him, and what we ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer by the loſs of him, <hi>under his ſhadow we ſhall,</hi> or we will, <hi>live among the heathen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this laſt hath been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by our ſelves: We have it <hi>Ex ore tuo,</hi> out of our own
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:153008:37"/>mouths, and out of theirs too, who it may be afterwards would have denied it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cui diximus,</hi> to whom, or of whom, we our ſelves have ſaid and acknowledged this.</p>
            <p>And when we have ſaid that, I wiſh we had no more to ſay of it: But there is that behind which cannot be concealed, and we muſt all of us lament, according to the tenour of the Text, and the duty of the Day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Captus eſt in laque is ipſorum, He was taken in their nets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I begin with the firſt Character of him, an endearing Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as I told you, he was <hi>the breath of our noſtrils.</hi> And what can be dearer to us then that? If our life be dear to us, our breath muſt needs be ſo; for we live no longer then we breath. God Almighty, when he made Man, <hi>He breathed into him the breath of life, and Man became a living ſoul,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:153008:38"/>Gen.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Inſpiravit in faciem ejus ſpiraculum vitae,</hi> there's the breath of life, and this God breathed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him; but before that he was not a living ſoul, but a lump of dead earth. 'Tis the breath of life that diſtinguiſheth us from the Clay that lies in the ſtreets.
<q>—Ex meliore luto.</q> 'Tis true, ſome men may be made of better Clay then others, but
'tis all Clay till the breath of life be breathed into us. Why then learn to value this breath, for then 'tis a living ſoul ſtraight. And this God inſpires, not onely into the firſt man, but into every man that comes into the World. And in this, that he might make Kings like himſelf, <hi>Dixi Dii eſtis,</hi> he is pleaſed to impart this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to them, that either they inſpire ſouls, or at leaſt they are the ſouls of their Subjects; for here he gives them ſuch an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute, <hi>Spiritus or is noſtri,</hi> they
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:153008:38"/>are <hi>the breath of our noſtrils.</hi> 'Tis ſaid of himſelf, <hi>In illo vivimus, In him we live, move, and have our being, Acts</hi> 17. and if Kings be <hi>the breath of our noſtrils,</hi> we live in them too. That they are ſo, the Prophet acknowledgeth it here, in behalf of all the People, who lived and breathed no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe but by him.
<q>— Quod ſpiro tuum eſt. —</q> We are beholding to him that we live, for it would not be <hi>vita vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talis</hi> without him. We were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be dead, then to live in ſlave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or miſery; and I appeal to all that hear me, what manner of life we lived after he was taken from us.</p>
            <p>But would any man be guilty of his own death, a <hi>Felo de ſe? No man ever hated his own fleſh,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5.29.</note> ſaith St. <hi>Paul;</hi> and therefore one would think no man ſhould hate his own Spirit, his Soul much leſs. Why the King is the Soul
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:153008:39"/>of every man; and would any man hate or hurt that? would he ſin againſt his own Soul ſo much, as to entertain the thought of any hurt toward him? If he do it, he ſins ſo: Firſt, becauſe the King is his Soul here, <hi>the</hi> very <hi>breath of his noſtrils:</hi> And, Secondly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his ſoul ſhall be ſure to be puniſhed for it hereafter, both bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſoul in Hell-fire.</p>
            <p>And yet for all this Kings are not ſecured from violence, though they are as near to us, and ſhould be as dear to us, as our ſouls.</p>
            <p>If we mark the Expreſſion, one would wonder how this ſhould come to paſs: To catch a Spirit in a Net, as 'tis here in the Text, <hi>Captus eſt in laqueis,</hi> a man can hardly conceive it. One may as ſoon paint a Voice, — <hi>Pinge ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> — as lay hold on a Spirit or a Breath. The Nets muſt be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fine, and artificially made, as
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:153008:39"/>the Poets feign of <hi>Vulcans</hi> Nets; and commonly there wants no Art in making of them, in which <hi>the breath of our noſtrils</hi> muſt be taken.</p>
            <p>But what pity is it that Kings are but a Breath? eſpecially good Kings, whom it doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the People that they ſhould be Immortal? <note place="margin">Pſal. 81.7.</note> 
               <hi>But ye ſhall dye like men,</hi> that's a ſad ſentence upon Princes. They that are the <hi>breath of our noſtrils,</hi> that the breath ſhould be in their noſtrils too, and they ſhould be no more then a Breath; this is but a ſad Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation upon it. And yet 'tis true, they are but Treaſure in Earthen Veſſels, when all's done no better then ordinary Pitchers, and as eaſily broken as any of them. And thence 'tis that we are bid to Ceaſe from them, <hi>Ceaſe ye from Man, <note place="margin">Iſa. 2.22.</note> whoſe breath is in his nostrils, for wherein is he to be accounted of?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:153008:40"/>
            <p>In the mean time to make no more of the breath of Princes, then we do of ordinary men, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of Murtherers and Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors, to take away their breath from them, and our own too, by violent hands; this addes to the Calamity much, and 'tis ſuch a frailty of Princes, which God and Nature never intended. For if they be <hi>the breath of our noſtrils,</hi> we muſt let them live as long as they can, <note place="margin">Quintil.</note> 
               <hi>Quorum accendit fragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litas pretium;</hi> like Cryſtal Glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, we ſhould be the more tender of them for that reaſon, leſt while we ſhorten their dayes, we ſhorten our own.</p>
            <p>And this is one of the Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives of Kings, That they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not dye alone, <note place="margin">Tert. Apol.</note> but <hi>Vobiſcum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutitur Imperium,</hi> in <hi>Tertullian:</hi> The Earthquake is univerſal, and all the People muſt dye with them;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſ. Antiq. lib.</hi> 17. <hi>c.</hi> 8.</note> 'tis fit they ſhould.
'Tis obſerved by Hiſtorians, <hi>Joſephus</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:153008:40"/>and others, That <hi>Herod</hi> the Great when he dyed, that he might be ſure the People ſhould make La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations at his Funeral, he took order that many of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of <hi>Iewry</hi> ſhould be put to death the ſame day with him: But it was a needleſs fear if his Government had been good. A King cannot go out of the world without the tears of his Subjects, becauſe they dye as well as he. Poſſibly there may be no Mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners becauſe there be no Men, all civilly dead, and none left to bury him, or to mourne for him: But elſe Mourners there muſt be enough, like the Daughters of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> whom Chriſt bids to weep for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as if all the men were ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely dead there, or were to dye ſhortly after, when Chriſt dyed that was their King. And therefore weep for your ſelves, and not for me; at your own
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:153008:41"/>Funerals, as often as a good King is buried. And ſo <hi>David</hi> lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed over <hi>Saul,</hi> though he was to ſucceed him in the Kingdom, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.17. 'tis one of the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons appointed for this day; and he bid them in the next Verſe, <hi>Teach their children the uſe of the Bow:</hi> That comes in by a <hi>Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis,</hi> and it ſeems at firſt ſight ſomewhat impertinent to the matter; but whatever the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per meaning of it may be, it might be to mind them, that now the King was dead, they might expect nothing but death too, and cutting of Throats; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they muſt ſtand upon their guards, and <hi>teach their children the uſe of the Bow. Behold, it is written in the book of Jaſher,</hi> as it follows; it ſtands upon Record there, as a thing worth the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring. And at the 24. Verſe it is, <hi>Ye daughters of Iſrael,</hi> again <hi>weep over Saul,</hi> as if the men
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:153008:41"/>were dead ſtill, <hi>who clothed you in Scarlet, with other delights, who put on ornaments of gold upon your apparel;</hi> and 'tis no wonder if the Women weep for the loſs of him then. But you ſee by all this what we loſe when we loſe a King, ſomething beſides Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and good Cloaths, even the better part of us, our Souls and Lives; when he dyes, all are civilly dead too, for he is <hi>Spiritus oris noſtri, The breath of our noſtrith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have done with the firſt Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a King, I come now to the ſecond.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Chriſtus Domini, The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed of the Lord.</hi> And that as I ſaid, is a ſacred expreſſion of him, for they were only ſacred per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that were wont to be <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed:</hi> Kings, Prieſts, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets all to be Anointed alike, and none were Anointed but them. Some men in the late times of Confuſion, while they
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:153008:42"/>made bold to take away the Hedge and Incloſure about the King, made bold to give a new Interpretation of that Text too, <hi>Touch not mine Anointed,</hi> and it muſt be not Kings only, but ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary perſons that were meant there. As they would have all the Lords people to be Prophets, and Prieſts, which are forbid to be touched too in that place, ſo they would have all the Lords people to be Kings, while they attributed this Title of Kings to them alſo: And all the Saints and ſervants of God, ſay they, are as much Gods Anointed as the King. For this Anointing is but <hi>Gratia gratis data,</hi> or <hi>Gratia Gratum faciens</hi> at moſt, ſome pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Gift or Grace in Gods Children, and ſo all are alike concerned in it, and ſo <hi>Ecce hic eſt Chriſtus,</hi> loe, here is Chriſt, here is Gods Anointed, and loe there, as it was in Chriſts own time ſo in
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:153008:42"/>ours, as many Chriſts or Anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ones as Chriſtians, and <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtos meos,</hi> concernes every body.</p>
            <p>But if you look into that Pſalm, you will find it otherwiſe, and who they were that were meant by it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.9, 10. Verſes, even the Patriarchs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by name, <hi>He made a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with</hi> Abraham, <hi>and an Oath unto</hi> Iſaac: <hi>And confirmed the ſame to</hi> Jacob <hi>for a Law, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Jacobs</hi> Children you know, were called the twelve Patriarchs, which afterward multiplyed into a Nation; But of them 'twas principally intended, and of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but by way of participati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in the opinion of all Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, till theſe new Glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s ſprung up like Gourds in a night; <hi>Touch not mine Anointed.</hi> And theſe Patriarchs we are to know, were Princes in their times, not onely as a Prince, <hi>Thou haſt power, thou haſt prevail'd with God, Ge.</hi> 42.28.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:153008:43"/>as 'twas ſaid of <hi>Jacob,</hi> but they were Princes indeed: 'Tis ſaid ſo of <hi>Abraham</hi> expreſly, <hi>Princeps Dei es apud nos, Thou art a Prince among us, Gen.</hi> 23.5. a Mighty Prince as we read it, and ſo he ſhewed himſelf, when he gave Battel and ſlew 4 Kings at once, <hi>Gen.</hi> 14. The like might be ſaid of <hi>Iſaac</hi> and the reſt of them; And their very name ſpeaks them to be ſuch, <hi>Patriar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chae,</hi> not onely Fathers, but Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in their Generations. And therefore <hi>Chriſtos meos,</hi> for all that can be ſaid to the contrary, will concern Kings ſtill.</p>
            <p>And Kings are Gods Anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted after a more peculiar manner: the Character they have here in the Text ſpeaks them ſo. 'Tis not <hi>Uncti,</hi> but <hi>Chriſti,</hi> they are called ſo here in the Text, and in that Pſalm too, <hi>Nolite tangere Chriſtos meos, Touch not my Chriſts.</hi> And not onely in that,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:153008:43"/>but in many other places which might be alleadged, 'tis applyed to Kings, and to Kings onely. As God is pleaſed to vouchſafe them his name, <hi>Dixi Dii eſtis,</hi> I have ſaid ye are Gods, ſo Chriſt vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafes them his, I have ſaid ye are Chriſts <hi>Meſsiahs,</hi> in the Hebrew, and <hi>Chriſti mei,</hi> my Chriſts in the Greek and Latine, and all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters tranſlate it ſo, not <hi>Uncti,</hi> but <hi>Chriſti.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why then this muſt make their perſons ſacred in a very high degree, not onely holy, but the holy of holies; as the inmoſt place of the Temple was, ſo is the perſon of the King. Let there be a Vaile between, as 'twas in the Temple, and no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane perſon come near him. His Sacred Majeſty is a Title that belongs to him without flattery. <hi>For 'tis holy oyle that he is Anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with, Pſal.</hi> 89.21. <hi>Oleo ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto meo, I have found</hi> David <hi>my
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:153008:44"/>ſervant, with my holy oyle have I Anointed him.</hi> And his Preſence was wont to be called <hi>Sacra veſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia,</hi> and his Writs <hi>Sacri Apices,</hi> holy almoſt every thing about him, and ſuch as ſhould beget a Reverence in the people.</p>
            <p>Since the foundations of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment were ſhaken, he that ſhall look back, and remember the Indignities that were put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the perſon of our late Dear Soveraigne, how every wicked and profane perſon did not onely touch him, which they are forbid to do in that Pſalm, but throng him and preſſe him too, as the Multitude did Chriſt; and that, not out of any affection to ſee him, but for worſe ends, which I had rather forget then mention, he will think the Reverence was loſt here, and the Anointing for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten in the Text. When eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hand was lifted up againſt him, ſo many hands at the Sentence,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:153008:44"/>and a hand to execute that upon the Scaffold, did they think the Lords Anointed was there, or did they remember the holy oyle at that time? Since all holy things were profaned, they made no reckoning of that, and therefore 'tis for the Intereſt of Princes to keep up the Value of holy things, and not to ſuffer them to be trampled upon by the Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude. But 'tis worth the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, which was ſaid of <hi>Saul</hi> in the Chapter before cited,
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 1.21.</note> 
               <hi>The ſhield of</hi> Saul <hi>was vilely caſt away, as though he had not been Anointed with oyle;</hi> And was not the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Head of the King it ſelf uſed ſo?
<q>—Horreſco referens,—</q> As if he had not been Anointed with oyle too, or as if never any ſuch Ceremony had been uſed. I would not be thought, <hi>Ambitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus in malis,</hi> or to aggravate the offences of any. For how can I?
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:153008:45"/>Language is too narrow for it.
<q>
                  <l>—Si Linguae Centum ſint,</l>
                  <l>Oraque Centum,—</l>
               </q> If I had as many Tongues as the Giant had hands, but <hi>Chriſtus Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini,</hi> was forgotten, that he was Anointed with oyle when thoſe hands were lifted up, and the Nets were ſet in the Text. If they had known, they would not have <hi>Crucifyed the Lord of life,</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Charity ſo far excuſed the <hi>Iews;</hi> and I am willing my Charity ſhould think the ſame of theſe: they did not know him at that time; in their practical un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding they did not; and 'twas a juſt Judgement of God upon them, for their ſhutting their eyes ſo long before, and their not knowing of him when they might. Well, <hi>Chriſtus Domini,</hi> I have ſaid enough upon that, that men may know him better hereafter, and take heed how they touch
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:153008:45"/>him. For the King is a Sacred perſon, <hi>The Anointed of the Lord,</hi> thats the ſecond Character of him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third is, <hi>In umbra tua vivemus, under his ſhadow we ſhall live among the Heathen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis no wonder, if we expect to live by him, <hi>for he is the breath of our noſtrils before,</hi> and I have ſaid enough of that already. <hi>But we ſhall live under his ſhadow,</hi> that ſpeaks the protection of a King. To live under his ſhadow, is to live under that. As Beaſts ſhelter themſelves under the ſhadow of a tree, ſo men are ſheltered under the protection of a King. You may have heard of the Royall Oak, or you have read the Dream of <hi>Nebuchadnezar,</hi> of a tree that reached to Heaven, and covered the Earth, under which the Beaſts of the field had ſhadow, and the Foules of the aire dwelt in the Boughes of it. And <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niels</hi>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:153008:46"/>Interpretation of it was this, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.22. <hi>Tu es Rex, it is thou O King, thy greatneſs reacheth to Heaven, and thy Dominion to the end of the Earth, and all had ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow and protection by it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What the benefit of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection is, we have known by the want of it; thoſe that live <hi>ſub Dio,</hi> that have no Canopy or Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering, but that of the Heavens, are expoſed to the injuries of all weather; whether it be hot or cold, wet or dry, they have no fence for it, but they muſt bear it out with head and ſhoulders, as we uſe to ſay. And this was our Caſe for many years together: what ſtorms have we endured? what miſeries have we felt? or what have we not felt rather? and all this for want of a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and of a Protector, and that ſhadow and comfort we might have enjoyed by him.</p>
            <p>We had indeed one at laſt that
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:153008:46"/>called himſelf ſo, a Protector he would needs be: but, alas! his ſhadow was but Mock-ſhade, or Night-ſhade rather, that was fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal and deadly to all that ſtood under it. <hi>Requieſcite ſub umbra mea,</hi> as the Bramble ſaid in <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thams</hi> Parable, <hi>Reſt under my ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow,</hi> when, alas! he had no ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow for them. Whereas the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of a lawful King is life to his Subjects; <hi>ſub umbra ejus vive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, Under his ſhadow we ſhall live. The ſun ſhall not burn thee by day, nor the moon by night,</hi> as 'tis <hi>Pſal.</hi> 121.6. <hi>He that dwells under the ſhadow of the moſt High,</hi> he hath thoſe privileges and many more, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.1. and ſo hath he that lives under the ſhadow of a lawful King; <hi>He ſhall defend thee under his wings,</hi> as 'tis there, <hi>and thou ſhalt be ſafe under his feathers;</hi> whereas they that want them have no ſafety at all, but are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed like ſo many Chickens to
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:153008:47"/>be a prey to the Kites.</p>
            <p>And what the pleaſure of the ſhade is in hot weather we all know, and moſt of us remember how happily we lived under it.
<q>— Hic nemus, hic ipſe tecum conſumerer avo.—</q> We could have been contented to live and dye under it too; but thus we lived for many years to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. We could not ſee when we were well, but out of the ſhade we would go, and out of Gods bleſſing into the warm Sun, and down goes the Tree himſelf, and farewell the ſhade of him; and what we got by it you all know.</p>
            <p>We are now by Gods bleſſing got into the ſhade again;
<q>— Non deficit alter amens.—</q> Another Tree is ſprung up from the ſame Root, God be thanked for it, and we will learn, I hope, to value the Tree better hereafter,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:153008:47"/>and the ſhadow we enjoy by him.</p>
            <p>But if we have no ſhadow, in what a caſe are we many times? <hi>Jonah</hi> will tell you, though it were but the ſhadow of a Gourd, and not of a Tree, that ſprung up and withered in a night, yet when he wanted it, and the Eaſt wind blew, and the Sun beat upon his head, then he wiſhed with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to dye ſtraight, and, <hi>it is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> ſayes he, <hi>to dye then to live, Ionah</hi> 4.8. And ſo 'tis, and the Bramble I told you of but now knew it, he that called himſelf Protector, and that there was no way to take the people better, then to ſay, Come under my ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow.</p>
            <p>Eſpecially if we conſider that which followes in the Text, <hi>Inter Gentes,</hi> that we live among the Heathen, as it was the caſe of the <hi>Iews</hi> here, they had many ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies about them, <hi>Aegyptians, Aſſyrians,</hi> and they that dwelt at
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:153008:48"/>
               <hi>Tyre,</hi> and I know not who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, that did but watch their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to make a prey of them. Therefore a Protector was neceſſary, and to have ſhelter and a ſhadow ſomewhere: and ſo 'twas for us, conſidering among whom we live, <hi>inter gentes,</hi> that we have Enemies round about us, Nations of a different Religion, or if of the ſame, that drive other Intereſts then ours, and therefore if not profeſſed Enemies, yet ſuſpected Friends at beſt, and therefore 'tis good to keep in the ſhade, not to loſe our Protector if we can chuſe.</p>
            <p>Well, we had him, and ſo had the <hi>Jews</hi> too, and we promiſed our ſelves all imaginable happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs under him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cui diximus, vivemus, Of whom we ſaid, We ſhall live under his ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow.</hi> This is but a Pathetical remembrance of their loſs, and the happineſs they enjoyed under
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:153008:48"/>their King: like Children that have loſt their Parents, or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents that have loſt their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, in whom they promiſed themſelves much Comfort and Content; but now they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of them.</p>
            <p>'Tis not good to ſet our hearts upon any thing in this world, leſt we lament the loſſe of it too ſoon, with a <hi>Cui diximus,</hi> we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed our ſelves ſuch and ſuch things by him.
<q>— At tibi ego Ignarus Thalamos,—</q> While we provide for our Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens Weddings, many times their friends come to their Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, and while we build upon the lives of our Parents, the Fathers of our Country, and make Pane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyricks upon Princes, we loſe them before the Speech is ended; ſuch is the frailty of humane things; <hi>Cui diximus vivemus, we ſaid, we ſhall live under their ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow,</hi> and we live to ſee them bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:153008:49"/>before us. Here we ſhould write Lamentations again, and we want a <hi>Jeremy</hi> to Weep it out.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Cui diximus, vivemus,</hi> minds us of ſome what elſe too, of Indignation, as well as of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation for a King. For 'tis not onely <hi>we ſhall,</hi> but <hi>we will live, Vivemus,</hi> the future tenſe both. And if we ſaid, <hi>we will live under his ſhadow,</hi> how came the Tree to be cut down?</p>
            <p>And this we all ſaid, as well as the <hi>Jows,</hi> we have it, <hi>Ex ore tuo,</hi> for them, and they for that King were guilty of no ſuch Cruelty. And ſo we had it out of our mouthes too; how many <hi>Hoſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nahs</hi> were ſung to this Bleſſed Saint and Martyr, immediately before the War: how many De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations of Loyalty, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him a Glorious King in it? And with the ſame Breath the Tree is blaſted, and afterward cut
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:153008:49"/>down by them. Well, this <hi>Cui diximus</hi> ſtands upon Record, to the Eternall Infamy of theſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricides, they themſelves ſaid it over and over, nay, they ſware it too in their Oaths of Allegeance to the King more then once, <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his ſhadow we will live,</hi> and yet they would not for all that, For</p>
            <p>I muſt come now to the laſt Act of the Tragedy, and I wiſh I could be excuſed from ſpeaking to it, becauſe no body would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, if we had not ſeen it Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before our eyes.</p>
            <p>But can any man believe it yet, or his own eyes, that believes what we have ſaid already, that he is <hi>ſpiritus oris noſtri,</hi> and <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus Domini,</hi> and <hi>in umbra ejus vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vemus, The breath of our noſtrils, the Anointed of the Lord, and we will live under his ſhadow,</hi> and yet that he ſhould read <hi>Captus eſt in Laqueis ipſorum,</hi> after all this
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:153008:50"/>he is taken in their Nets.</p>
            <p>If you underſtand it of <hi>Joſiah</hi> or <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> are to be excuſed from it: For they were guilty of no ſuch wickedneſſe, as I ſaid but now. 'Tis true, <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah</hi> was ſlain at <hi>Megiddo,</hi> and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the Nets of <hi>Pharaoh Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho,</hi> and ſo was <hi>Zedekiah</hi> taken in the Nets of the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> and carryed Captive to <hi>Babylon,</hi> but his own ſubjects had no hand in it. They lamented his loſſe; <hi>Ieremy</hi> here doth it in the name of all the people, who could have been contented to live under his ſhadow, and though he was none of the beſt Kings neither.</p>
            <p>But if you will have it to be a Prophecy, and underſtand it of Chriſt, then indeed the <hi>Iews</hi> were Regicides too. Will ye Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy your Ring? <hi>Pilate</hi> asked them that Queſtion, and they ſaid they would; <hi>anguis ejus ſuper nos, his bloud be upon us, and upon our Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:153008:50"/>
            <p>Well, though in the Propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ſenſe of the Text, the Paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel hold good, and the <hi>Iews</hi> were as bad as any of us, yet in the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terall ſenſe they were better, <hi>In laqueis ipſorum,</hi> muſt be meant of the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> or <hi>Pharaoh Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho,</hi> and not of the <hi>Iews.</hi> But in the Prophetical ſenſe, the <hi>Iews</hi> cannot waſh their hands of it nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. No more can ſome of us, from being as bad as any <hi>Iew</hi> of them all. And <hi>In laqueis ipſorum,</hi> brings it home to our Regicides too; Therefore let them take it among them, <hi>In their Nets the Lords Anointed was taken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theirs! what would ſome men give now to be excuſed from this? Why, any bodies ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then Theirs. Theirs, that is, the Nets of ſome Forraign Enemie, if you will, of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions among whom they lived in the Text, ſuch threds ſhould be ſpun abroad by <hi>Pharaoh Necho,</hi> or
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:153008:51"/>the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> by <hi>Almaynes,</hi> or <hi>Italians,</hi> or <hi>Spaniards,</hi> or ſome ſtrange Nation.
<q>—Hoſtium tell us habet,—</q> But I hope they live not in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> 'tis no Home-made-Cloth, or Thred either. And yet it is for all that <hi>Ipſorum,</hi> we can car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it no further, then to the Doors of our next Neighbours, thoſe that breathed by him, and lived by him, under his ſhadow, and under his Protection: <hi>Ipſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> is Latin for Engliſh-men, <hi>In their Nets he was taken,</hi> to revive again an obſolete Obſervation long out of date with us, to the diſhonour of the Nation, as if the Kings of <hi>England</hi> were Kings of Devils, and not of men.</p>
            <p>But what? In the Nets of his own ſubjects? Can they juſtifie a War againſt their King? Indeed the Threds of this Net, the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of Rebellion, and depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and Murthering of Princes
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:153008:51"/>were firſt ſpun abroad in the ſhops of the <hi>Jeſuites.</hi> And ſince I know not how, we are more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in them then they. As 'tis with many other Commodities, for which we were at firſt behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our Neighbours, but now we make them as well at home, they be grown ſtaple with us; ſo you may have theſe now in every Weavers ſhop, as well as in the <hi>Jeſuites.</hi> They will tell you in plain Engliſh, for, <hi>In ordine ad ſpiritualia,</hi> hath been tranſlated into all Languages, that to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the Kingdom of Chriſt, that is, their own Kingdom and not his, and to promote the Cauſe, 'tis lawful to take Armes, to Murther Kings, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any Villany in the world. And yet St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, that no Cauſe will juſtifie this: He Preaches ſubjection to Princes, <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore every body much more: and
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:153008:52"/>they that reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelves Damnation.</hi> And ſo St. <hi>Peter</hi> Preaches the ſame, and the Primitive Fathers of the Church after them, as, if we had ſo much leaſure, 'twere very eaſie to ſhew you. I will inſtance one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in two, one of the Greek Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and one of the Latin. St. <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> for the Greek, and he ſayes, that when <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate had deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Ruine of the Chriſtians, he was diſappointed only by their Teares, <note place="margin">Naz. Orat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. in Juli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anum.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, they made uſe of no other Weapons againſt the perſecutor but Tears, and yet almoſt all his Army were Chriſtians. And ſo St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in the like Caſe, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Orat. in Auxent.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Dolere potero, potero flere, I can weep and lament,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>but I cannot reſiſt; Nec poſſum nec debeo, I ought not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt it if I could.</hi> Theſe were all the Nets thoſe Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:153008:52"/>made uſe of, to catch and Embalme their Perſecutors in their Teares, like a flie in a drop of <hi>Amber.</hi> But for any other Nets they never knew the uſe of them, till theſe late Modern times, wherein many new Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are diſcovered, and this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt, for ſubjects to make Nets for their Kings.</p>
            <p>But this, I muſt tell you, is in Invention deviating from Juſtifie and Right, as the Wiſe man ſayes there, <hi>God made man upright, but he hath ſought out many Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> they are but crooked ones, as many turnings in them, as in a Labyrinth, and the upright man whom God made, will never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with them; for they are Nets of their own making, and not his. And they be made to a miſchievous end, to catch the feet of Princes.</p>
            <p>Mighty Hunters it ſeems they are, like <hi>Nimrod,</hi> that no prey
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:153008:53"/>will ſerve them but their King. Why ordinary Hunters <hi>Moll ort praeda ſaginantur,</hi> as 'tis in <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillian,</hi> and ſo ordinary Dogs too,
<q>—Praeda Canum Lepus eſt,—</q> A Hare will ſerve their turn. Theirs was the Lion, a ſport, if I may call it ſo, not uſuall among us in <hi>England,</hi> what ever it may be among <hi>Africans</hi> or <hi>Indians.</hi> But ſo it muſt be,
<q>—Placet in vulnus—Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Cervix.</q> And they lov'd the ſport too wel, a Company of Hell-hounds they were; and you cannot but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it, to go a King-catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, with Reverence be it ſpoken by us to the Sacred Majeſty of Kings, 'twas their paſtime, as well to talk of it, as to act it.</p>
            <p>And how often their Nets were ſet for him, 'twould be but a ſad ſtory to repeat. As the Devil ſets Nets every where,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:153008:53"/>
               <hi>Totus mundus Diaboli Laqueus,</hi> ſayes St. <hi>Gregory,</hi> ſo did theſe men too. He could not ſet his foot in any corner of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, but there was a Net ſet for him. <hi>They have ſet traps in my way, and in the way wherein I went, have they privily laid a ſnare for me,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> complained, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 142.3. Hunted he was from one place to another, till at laſt he fell into the Nooſe, and <hi>Captus eſt in Laqueis ipſorum, he was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in their Nets.</hi> He that ſhall remember how he came into our Neighbour Iſland, by a Train, and how faſt they held him there when they had him, cannot think this Text ill applyed, but he will look upon it as a Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of him too.</p>
            <p>But yet take him alive for all that;
<q>— <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, —</q> as he ſaid to <hi>Agamemnon:</hi> though you have hunted for him, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:153008:54"/>him, yet deſtroy him not. <hi>Zedekiah</hi> was not deſtroyed, though he were taken. A living Dog is better then a dead Lion; they did what they could to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a Dog before him, for he muſt not live.
<q>— Timete ſuperi fata. —</q> Here's the heighth of all Impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: Next to the Crucifying of Chriſt the King of Heaven, I chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge any Hiſtory to match it; for he was deſtroyed not in Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, as <hi>David</hi> ſaid of <hi>Saul, Forte in praelium deſcendens peribit, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure he may fall in the battel;</hi> and ſo there might be ſomething of Chance in it, and not of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, becauſe Bullets diſtinguiſh not; Not by the hands of a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Aſſaſſinate, as ſome other Princes have miſcarryed, but as they would have the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, by the hand of Juſtice. That he might be like his Saviour in all things, he muſt be arraigned, but
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:153008:54"/>before worſe Judges then <hi>Pilate;</hi> for he cryed, <hi>What evill hath he done?</hi> and ſo waſhed his hands, for a teſtimony that he would have no hand in ſhedding the blood of Chriſt; whereas theſe waſhed their hands in his blood: they held up their hands to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Sentence, and with their hands ſubſcribed the Sentence of Death.</p>
            <p>And ſo 'twas acted accordingly. Will Poſterity believe it?
<q>— Nec audent Fata tam vaſtum nefas — Admittere.—</q> Yet ſo it was, a Scaffold erected at the Court gate, <hi>In ludibrium Majeſtatis,</hi> in defiance of Majeſty, and the King was murdered at high Noon. And 'tis ſaid there was a Net upon the Scaffold too, in caſe of reſiſtance, to make good the <hi>Captus in laqueis</hi> in every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, though this Lamb before the Shearers gave them no occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to make uſe of it.</p>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:153008:55"/>
            <p>And by this time I ſuppoſe it may be ſull Sea with you, and you call for juſtice upon the Murtherers. They have felt it ſome of them, and they have ſuffered deſervedly for it; the ſtroke of Juſtice found them out at laſt, and Gods Providence is magnified in his care of humane affairs.</p>
            <p>But while we call for juſtice upon others, are we our ſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent?
<q>—Ne ſaevi magne ſacerdos.—</q> Something there is in the Text yet, that may draw us into the Conſpiracy too, as well as we think of our ſelves, and as ſevere as we are to other men.</p>
            <p>If the Vulgar Tranſlation read the Text right, inſtead of <hi>Captus eſt in laqueis ipſoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> it is there <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt in poccatis noſtris,</hi> He was taken, not in <hi>their Nets,</hi> but in <hi>our ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Murther, they ſay, will out;
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:153008:55"/>and then though ſome have been puniſhed already, yet there be many more that deſerve it; and we our ſelves are of that number. Talk no more of the <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents,</hi> or the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> or the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> or any Sectary be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the Net was ſpun by all of us, in our ſins he was taken.</p>
            <p>And 'tis moſt true; A good King cannot miſcarry, but for the ſins of the people. If you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it of <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> this reading of the Text proves it. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the advice is good in <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian, Eſto tu Religioſus in Deum, <note place="margin">Ter. Apol.</note> ſi vis illum propitium Imperatori;</hi> the way to preſerve a good King, is to be good our ſelves; and for a bad one, 'tis as true, that he miſcarries ſeldom but upon that account. To look no further then <hi>Zedekiah</hi> in the Text, that you may be ſatisfyed, the people ſpun the Net in which he was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, as well as himſelf, look into
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:153008:56"/>the 36. <hi>chap.</hi> of the ſecond of <hi>Chro. ver.</hi> 14. there you ſhall meet with a <hi>Moreover,</hi> like an <hi>Inſuper,</hi> after an account, after he had ſpoken of <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> what he was, and what befell him in that Chapter, <hi>Moreover,</hi> ſayes the Text, <hi>All the chief of the Prieſts, and the people tranſgreſſed very much, and he ſent his Meſſengers and they deſpiſed them, therefore he brought upon them the King of the Chaldees;</hi> and therefore 'tis true which the Prophet ſayes here, and 'tis the beſt reading of the Text, <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt in peccatis noſtris, The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſins were the chiefeſt Nets, in which the King was taken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And they be very ſtrong ones. When the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> are upon him, no <hi>Sampſon</hi> can break them, but his ſtrength then is no more then an ordinary mans.</p>
            <p>Why, if that be true, what have we to ſay for our ſelves? ſuppoſe we were now at the Bar
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:153008:56"/>of Gods Juſtice, though the Clemency of the King hath par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned us here, and we were Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned for the Murther of his Father; I ſay, what have we to ſay for our ſelves?
'Twould be in vain to plead Not Guilty, and to lay the fault upon others, for <hi>Captus eſt in peccat is noſtris</hi> will confute us, and ſo far reconcile all parties, <hi>He was taken in our ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But our beſt defence would be a penitent Confeſſion of the fact.
<q>—Me, me, adſum,—qui feci,—</q> It is I that have ſinned, but theſe Sheep, what have they done? And thoſe Wolves too that tore him in pieces, what have they done more then any of us? It is uſually ſaid, one of the Adverſe parties held the King by the Haire, while the other cut off his Head. That the former of theſe take it not ill, we will allow them more Company; for alas!
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:153008:57"/>we held him as well as they. We were not upon the Scaffold to hold him; no more were they. But we were ſomewhere elſe. Like Witches, that can kill a man and never come near him.
<q>Necte tribus nodis.—</q> So we might tie knots, or thruſt pins into him, and yet ſit at home by the fire, or upon our Thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſholds, and never come ſo near him as to touch his haire at all.</p>
            <p>Beloved, I hope no body will take it ill, that I make ſuch a Compariſon, or rank thoſe that were the Kings good ſubjects, with thoſe that were not ſo. But it would be thought upon ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly by every one of us, and this day eſpecially more then up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any other, how far every one of our particular ſins contributed to the death of our King.</p>
            <p>There be many Threds, you know, that muſt go to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king up of a Net. And if it be a
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:153008:57"/>Net with Cords, as it muſt be a ſtrong one for ſuch a purpoſe as this, to take the feet of a King in, there muſt be many more.</p>
            <p>Therefore let's conſider, what particular ſins we our ſelves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to the heap, and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of this Net. For I will not mention thoſe ſins which were almoſt Epidemical to the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, our Compliances and ſilence when we ſaw the Thieves come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the Murtherers ſetting their Nets for the King, we did not cry out as we ſhould have done, and ſo we were Acceſſaries, at leaſt, Conſenters; we ſaw a Thief and conſented unto him by our ſilence, if not principals as they were. And in Crimes of this high nature, Felony and Treaſon, the Law ſayes all are Principalls; but our Luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmeneſſe in Religion, neither hot nor cold, like the <hi>Laodiceans,</hi> the neglect of our Duties in our
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:153008:58"/>ſeverall Stations, both Lay-men and Clerks, our Swearing, our Drunkenneſſe, our Profaneneſs, our Pride, our Covetouſneſſe, our Envy, our Malice, our Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting; all theſe, and many, infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely many more put together, will make a Net with a witneſſe; 'tis more then a threefold Cord, and 'tis no wonder if the feet of the beſt King in the world were taken in them.</p>
            <p>Let us ſit down and lament this day, for the wickedneſſes we our ſelves were, and I doubt it ſtill are, guilty of. We ſee what a Thred we have ſpun, to the cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off the life of a King: And can we think to eſcape without Repentance? or becauſe the <hi>Gali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laeans</hi> or ſome others were greater ſinners then we, therefore we are none at all? I tell you, nay, <hi>but except ye repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though you were none of the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:153008:58"/>Kings Judges, nor his Accuſers, nor ever were in Armes againſt him, or gave any countenance to the Rebellion; yet like the Witches I told you of, you might contrive his miſchief at home; ſo you did, in your Parlours, in your Cloſets, in your Shops, and in your Chambers.</p>
            <p>And therefore <hi>Enter into your chambers again, be ſtill, and conſider this;</hi> for your own ſakes, for the ſake of Gods Anointed, leſt you bring him into the Net too: And nothing elſe can do it,
<q>Bella Telemacho paras,—</q> And if you love the King think of it, for ſurely <hi>Thou alſo art one of them,</hi> and ſo was I, and every one of us; we may be kin to, and love the Traytor, though we hate the Treaſon never ſo much. But let us all ſhew ſome ſeverity againſt our ſelves too, to put away Gods wrath from the Nation; ſome vindicative juſtice in our tears
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:153008:59"/>and abſtinences this day, as it hath fallen upon others in a ſeverer manner.</p>
            <p>And then God will have mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy upon us, he will keep the feet of his Anointed out of the Nets of wicked men, he will preſerve this Church and Kingdom from violence, and he will bring us to his Kingdom in Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which God grant, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:153008:59"/>
            <head>A Sermon preached in the Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dral Church of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> on <hi>Feb. 24. 1661.</hi> at the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſizes held there.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ISAIAH 1.26.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Et reſtituam judices tuos ut fuerunt prius, &amp; conſiliarios tuos ſicut antiquitus: poſt haec voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beris civitas juſti, urbs fidelis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And I will reſtore thy judges as at the firſt, and thy counſellors as at the beginning: afterward thou ſhalt be called the city of righteouſneſs, the faithful city.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>T reſtituam judices tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os.</hi> Here's a Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration promiſed in the Text, and that implies a Deſolation before; if you look back to the 7. Verſe of the Chapter, you ſhall find it ſo, <hi>Terra veſtra de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerta, Your country is deſolate, your
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:153008:60"/>cities are burnt with fire.</hi> There's as much deſolation as the fire could make; and the ſword no doubt did its part too, <hi>for ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers devoure your land,</hi> in that Verſe; and in the next Verſe, <hi>Sion is left as a cottage, and as a lodge in a garden of Cucumbers.</hi> And <hi>if the Lord of hoſts had not left us a very ſmall remnant, we ſhould have been as Sodom, and we ſhould have been like unto Gomor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah,</hi> Verſe 9. and that ſpeaks de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation again.</p>
            <p>One of the chief ſins that brought it upon them was the <hi>perverting of judgment,</hi> at the 21. Verſe. How is the faithful City become a Harlot? It was full of Judgment, Righteouſneſs lodged in it, but now Murtherers, <hi>Nunc autem homicidae;</hi> Murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers were got into the Judges room; and then the beſt of them were no better then <hi>companions of thieves,</hi> Verſe 23. Conſenters at
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:153008:60"/>leaſt, while they loved Gifts and followed after Rewards, and refuſed to judge the Fatherleſſe, or to let the Cauſe of the Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow come before them.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the people were but in a ſad condition, you will believe. And no ſooner had God eaſed himſelf of his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries at the 24. Verſe, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently he had compaſſion on them, with the turn of a hand as it were, <hi>Et convertam manum, I will turn my hand upon thee, and purely purge away thy Droſſe, and take away all thy Tinne,</hi> at the Verſe immediately before the Text. And when that's done, the greateſt inſtance of his Mercy was this,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Et restituam judices tuos, And I will reſtore thy judges as at the firſt, and thy counſellors as at the beginning: afterward thou ſhalt be called the city of righteouſneſs, the faithful city.</hi> Where</p>
            <pb n="114" facs="tcp:153008:61"/>
            <p>Firſt, we have as I told you, a Reſtauration promiſed, <hi>Et reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuam,</hi> that's the firſt thing: take the perſon with it, for 'tis Gods doing and not mans, <hi>I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the perſons reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Thoſe are of very great conſideration in a Community, <hi>Judices tuos, &amp; conſiliaries tuos, Thy Judges and thy Counſellors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Qualification of the perſons, they muſt be, <hi>Ut fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt prius, &amp; ſicut antiquitus,</hi> none of the new Module, or fitted for a new fangled Government, <hi>But thy judges as at the firſt, and thy counſellors as at the beginning.</hi> And this gives</p>
            <p>A new name to the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as if they were new Chriſtned by good Judges and faithfull Counſellors, <hi>Afterward thou ſhalt be called the city of righteouſneſs, the faithful city.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I begin with the Reſtauration
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:153008:61"/>as it is promiſed here, <hi>Et reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, And I will reſtore.</hi> This re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring is an Act of infinite Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in God, conſidering how all the world is ſet upon Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Deſolation. The Devil himſelf is called the deſtroyer, <hi>Abaddon,</hi> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 9.11. The exterminating Angel: but when he was gone, <hi>Vae unum abiit,</hi> follows upon it, one woe went with him. And no wonder then if wicked men be of the ſame Trade with the Devil, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in nothing but Deſtruction. <hi>Deſtruction and unhappineſs is in their wayes, Pſal.</hi> 14. 'Tis a roade they can never get out of, a way they have to deſtroy themſelves, and, if they can, to deſtroy others with them.</p>
            <p>He that ſhall look over the World, and conſider what Deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations have been made in every corner of it at one time or other, will ſee the print of the Devils
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:153008:62"/>foot in all places, and that the deſtroyer hath been there.</p>
            <p>Even in the holy places them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. When ye ſhall ſee the Abomination of Deſolation ſtanding in the holy place, That we have ſeen in this, and many other places beſides; the Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of Deſolation got into Churches, no place could be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed from Violence; but then 'twas time to flie into the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and every body to ſhift for himſelf. 'Tis a complaint the Prophet makes of ſuch men as Theſe, <hi>Locum ejus deſolaverunt, For they have devoured Jacob, <note place="margin">Pſal. 79.7.</note> and laid waſte his dwelling place.</hi> And if they make thus bold with Gods houſe, 'tis no wonder if they make no bones of devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring one another, and there be a Deſolation in other places too. A very Wilderneſſe every place was become; <hi>God ſuſtained his own people forty yeares in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe,</hi>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:153008:62"/>and we have been ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained half that time here: In a Wilderneſſe where there hath been nothing but Deſolation and Deſtruction in every corner of the Land.</p>
            <p>If there were not a time to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtones in <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> as well as there is a time to caſt them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and a time to Plant, as well as to pull up that which is Plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, we might look for a Deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion indeed, and that there would not be one ſtone left upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; not onely in the Temple, but in the City, yea and in the Country too: And this time of gathering and planting is Gods time, the time of pulling up and eradicating is the Devils and Wicked mens. Root and Branch! Unmerciful men, that could think of ſuch an eradicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as that was. <hi>Charitas autem Aedificat:</hi> Surely there was no Charity among them.</p>
            <pb n="118" facs="tcp:153008:63"/>
            <p>Well, 'twas time God ſhould think of Planting and Reſtoring, leſt all ſhould have become an abſolute Wilderneſs indeed. And God takes upon him this Work, <hi>He that is the repairer of the Brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, that is reſolved to ſave you, and to build the Cities of Judah, Pſal.</hi> 102. That ſayes to <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, Thou ſhalt be inhabited, and to the Cities of Iudah, Ye ſhall be built, and I will raiſe up the decayed places thereof, Iſa.</hi> 44.26.</p>
            <p>This is a work proper for God Almighty. 'Tis an eaſie thing to pull down, every hand can do that, like Scholars that may be perfect in the Analyticks, and 'tis all the Logick moſt men have. But to compoſe and put toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that requires Skill and Strength in the Architect. He muſt be a wiſe builder, as 'twas ſaid of him in the Goſpel; and ſo he muſt be Strong and Rich, and have many other Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:153008:63"/>beſides; leſt it be ſaid of him as 'tis there in that Chapter, <hi>This man began to build, and was not able to finiſh,</hi> St. <hi>Luke</hi> 14.30. That's the caſe of many in the world, they are not able to finiſh. God is, he is Omnipotent, able to finiſh, and willing to finiſh too.</p>
            <p>Therefore he delights in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king. And if he had not made the World, it had not been made till this time: And if he had not made every thing that's in it, it had lain in its firſt <hi>Chaos</hi> ſtill. But there is a Chapter of the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in <hi>Geneſis,</hi> and St. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſums it up in a Verſe: <hi>Omnia per ipſum facta ſunt, All things were made by him, and without him was made nothing that was made,</hi> St. <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.3. As all things were made by him, ſo all things were marred by the Devil. And therefore it muſt be the ſame hand again to reſtore, as well as to make.</p>
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:153008:64"/>
            <p>And that keeps God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty alwaies imployed, <hi>Pater meus operatur uſque adhuc,
<note place="margin">Jo. 5.17.</note> My Father worketh hitherto, and I work, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring and repairing the breaches which the Devil and wicked men make in the world.</hi> And till the time of the Reſtitution of all things be come, he will never be at reſt, but he is mending and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of ſome thing or other ſtill. <hi>And then at the day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there will be a reſtitution of all things,</hi> Acts 3.21.</p>
            <p>But this <hi>all things</hi> is but a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall expreſſion of Gods making and reſtoring. And we have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of nothing but things hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that have come into Gods hands, whether to be made or made again. But what ſay we to perſons then? They are more conſiderable then any thing elſe certainly. The King of <hi>Sodom</hi> was of that mind: <hi>Give me the perſons,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 14.21.</note> ſayes he, <hi>take the goods to
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:153008:64"/>thy ſelf.</hi> And perſons are of more value then any goods, and may do more hurt or good in the world; eſpecially ſuch perſons as they may be. The Sun is not more neceſſary then ſome men: and they that take them away, do as good as <hi>Tollere ſolem,</hi> in the Orators phraſe, take the Sun out of the World. Therefore the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of ſuch is as great a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy as the making of a <hi>New Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and a new Earth,</hi> for when we have that, that which St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> ſayes we look for, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13. There ſhall but dwell righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs there; and when we have theſe, the perſons promiſed in the Text, <hi>There will be a city of righteouſneſs here.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore 'tis time we come to conſider the perſons, and they indeed are moſt worthy our conſideration, who bring ſuch a bleſſing as that with them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Iudices tuos, &amp; conſiliaries
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:153008:65"/>tuos, Thy judges, and thy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thy judges</hi> firſt. And that takes in the Supreme Judge as well as the Subordinate. And the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> you know were gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Judges as well as Kings, ſuch as had the Soveraign Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er inveſted in their perſons, therefore to reſtore thy Judges will take in the Supreme Judge with them.</p>
            <p>And ſo 'tis. <note place="margin">Pro. 8.15.</note> 
               <hi>By me Kings raign, and Princes execute judgement.</hi> 'Tis the imployment of Kings to execute Judgement, and the Judges to execute it in their names. Therefore among the Judges that are reſtored, we muſt look with an awefull Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence upon the Supreme Judge firſt, and adore the goodneſſe of God in the Reſtauration of him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Et reſtituam judices,</hi> God hath made his word good in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:153008:65"/>of the King; for, as God ſits in the Congregation of the Princes, and is a Judge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Gods; ſo the King ſits in the Congregation of the Judges, and he is a Judge among them. And this Judge God hath reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to us, and of all Acts of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Reſtauration in God, none was ever greater then this. We ſee it, and it is marvellous in our eyes; but how he came to be reſtored God Almighty onely knows, for he onely did it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ego reſtituam,</hi> here comes in the perſon; as it was in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of man, he conſulted onely with himſelf, <hi>faciamus,</hi> He, and the other perſons of the bleſſed Trinity; ſo 'twas in the reſtoring and making again of the King. He conſulted not with fleſh and bloud, as 'tis there, nor did he make uſe of any arme or hand but his own; it was he that made him, and reſtored him, and not
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:153008:66"/>we, or any body elſe. And ſo God takes it to himſelf here, <hi>I will reſtore him, Ut non glorietur omnis caro,</hi> that no fleſh ſhould boaſt in his preſence, nor the glory of it be given to any body elſe.</p>
            <p>And yet I know there be ſome that do boaſt of it, and think 'twas a work highly meritorious in themſelves. If they did it, I do not envy them the glory of it. But they ſhould remember the flie upon the Axel-tree, and that the duſt was raiſed by ſome body elſe. Even by him that took off the wheels of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Chariots, that they drove heavily; ſo he threw duſt in the eyes of our dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, that they could not ſee, nor underſtand one another; and ſo the King was reſtored before they themſelves were aware of it. But I had rather look upon God in this action, then admire the greatneſs of a flie through any
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:153008:66"/>Multiplying-glaſſes whatſoever. <hi>Ego restituam judices, I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore thy judges:</hi> That for the perſons reſtoring.</p>
            <p>But in the Reſtauration of the King, the Judges were reſtored too. And a Reſtauration of both was very neceſſary. I know we had Judges when we had no King, and ſo we had Counſellors too. They know beſt from whom they had their Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and I have no Authority to examine that, or to ask the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>Quis te conſtituit judicem, Who made thee a judge?</hi> 'Tis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for us that now we are ſure we have Judges lawfully called. The great Thieves do not lead away the leſs now, as the Philoſopher ſaid once, but we have Judges of Gods and the Kings making.</p>
            <p>And what a bleſſing is it that we have them? If by Judges here we underſtand the Civil
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:153008:67"/>Magiſtrate at large, as ſome In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters do, all thoſe that do not affect Anarchy, and to live under no Government, muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the neceſſity of them. <hi>But every man did what was good in his own eyes,</hi> was no great commendation of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, or of the no-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment rather, when 'twas ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>In thoſe dayes there was no King in Iſrael.</hi> And you may ſee what were the effects of it in the Verſe before, <hi>The man Micah had a houſeful of Gods, there Idolatry crept in, and he conſecrated one of his Sons who became a Prieſt,</hi> 'tis in the Book of <hi>Judges</hi> Chapter 17. Verſe 5. But a Prieſt He was of his own making: there was another encroachment, ſuch as we had many, but without any Conſecration at all, when there was no King with us. They did what they could to have no Prieſts neither; and in a little
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:153008:67"/>time more we ſhould have had no Religion; for when he is gone that is the keeper of the Tables, as the King is, what wonder is it if the Tables themſelves be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, the Laws of God and man violated, and there be neither Religion nor Honeſty in the world? This is the fruit of no King, and of no Government in a Nation. Anabaptiſts and other Fanatical perſons may like it. But we have felt the ſmart of it, and therefore we gratefully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the benefit of reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the King and the lawful Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate to us.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Reſtituam judices</hi> points more particularly to them, whoſe peculiar Office it is to judge: And then what greater bleſſing can be given to a Nation then this? To ſend down Juſtice again from Heaven, which ſeemed to have taken her Farewell of the world before;
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:153008:68"/>
               <q>— Terras Aſtraea reliquit. —</q> She was abſolutely gone and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken her flight; and now to ſee her reſtored again, to have her brought home to our very doors, by Judges <hi>as at the firſt;</hi> who can look upon this but as a bleſſing from Heaven? Righteouſneſs ſhall go before him, <note place="margin">Pſ. 85.11.</note> 
               <hi>and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs ſhall look down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> whither ſhe was gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. This is a Reſtauration of Juſtice worthy of God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty.</p>
            <p>Why then, <hi>Salve juſtitia,</hi> as 'tis ſaid of the Emperor <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cam. Hiſt. Med. lib.</hi> 4.</note> That he was wont to vail his Bonnet as often as he paſſed by any place of Execution, and cry, <hi>God maintain juſtice;</hi> ſo we that are Subjects, and have much more need of juſtice then the King hath, ſhould ſay the like, and bid Juſtice welcome home, that hath been a ſtranger amongſt us ſo many years. And ſo we
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:153008:68"/>ſhould kiſs the feet of thoſe that bring it, the Judges that God promiſeth to reſtore here: They are a ſecond ſort of Evangeliſts, they bring glad ridings of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, that's as good as Peace; for <hi>Righteouſneſs and Peace kiſs each other</hi> too, and therefore let us thankfully kiſs the feet of them that bring both; for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Righteouſneſs there would be no Peace: <hi>Magnaregna</hi> would be but <hi>magna latrocinia,</hi> ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Park-Corners every place in the Kingdom would be, and there would be no more ſecurity in the City then in the Countrey; for Juſtice was exiled from both: And thoſe petty <hi>Nimrods</hi> that hunt and take Purſes upon the High-way, would take them in the High-ſtreets too, in <hi>Cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide,</hi> if there were no juſtice to keep them in awe.</p>
            <p>But remember, that <hi>for all theſe things God will bring thee to
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:153008:69"/>judgment;</hi> if it be but in the next world 'tis enough to cool the courage of any <hi>Hector</hi> of them all: And then much more if it be in this. For moſt men can be contented to truſt God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with their Souls, that dare not truſt an Earthly Judge with their Bodies: And though they are forbid to fear them, that is, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratively more then God, <hi>that can caſt both body and ſoul into Hell-fire,</hi> yet they are awed onely with thoſe that can kill the body. And if he be in the literal ſenſe, <hi>Judex ante oſtium,</hi> if the Judge ſtand before the door, 'tis the greateſt ſecurity that there will be peace and quietneſſe in the houſe.</p>
            <p>For men are not good but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their wills. <note place="margin">Rom. 13.4.</note> 
               <hi>Then fear,</hi> that's a greater Bridle to reſtrain us from evil, then all the Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the world; for <hi>he beareth not the ſword in vain.</hi> 'Tis the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:153008:69"/>Sword that keeps the world in awe, Rewards will not do it: but while there is a Sword-bearer, and he bears him not in vain; <hi>then fear,</hi> and in the mean time honeſt men may walk the ſtreets without fear.</p>
            <p>But without Juſtice they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. 'Tis ſo neceſſary in a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, that thoſe that are the greateſt Violators of Juſtice, Thieves and Robbers themſelves cannot be without it, <hi>Ne illi qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem qui ſcelere paſcuntur,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Off. l.</hi> 2.</note> ſayes <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero,</hi> They that live upon Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing and Stealing; yet they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not live <hi>ſine particula juſtitiae,</hi> there muſt be ſomething of juſtice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them: He that robs or ſteals from his fellow, ſayes he, ſhall be turned out of the Frater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and be ſuffered to rob no more. And there be <hi>Leges latro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> certain Laws among them, which they themſelves require to be obſerved: and ſome that
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:153008:70"/>were more honeſt then the reſt, were famous for the obſerving of them: He inſtances in <hi>Vargu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> and <hi>Viriatus,</hi> which laſt was not leſs famous for his juſtice, then that a <hi>Roman</hi> Army was fain to be ſent out to ſuppreſs him. But though <hi>when Thieves fall out, honeſt men may hope to come to their goods,</hi> yet they themſelves muſt look to be undone by it; and if <hi>Satan be divided againſt himſelf, his Kingdom. cannot stand,</hi> no more can the Kingdom of men neither; but there muſt be Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Righteouſneſs in them, or elſe all muſt come to confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: If <hi>we look for judgment, and there be none; we may look for ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation too, but it will be far from us, Iſa.</hi> 59.10. But if Oppreſſion come in the room of it, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Righteouſneſs if there be a Cry, <hi>Ecce clamor,</hi> as 'tis there; if ſuch Weeds, or Brambles ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſpring up in the Vineyard
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:153008:70"/>inſtead of it, though it be the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> it ſelf, <hi>Gods own vineyard, Iſa.</hi> 5.7. yet <hi>Auferam ſepem ejus</hi> will follow upon it, <hi>I will take away the hedge thereof, and it ſhall be laid waſte.</hi> And therefore to prevent that, and to preſerve the Hedges and Inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum,</hi> which muſt be preſerved if we will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve any thing, unleſs we will turn Levellers again, and lay all in common, which you ſee God laid as a judgment upon <hi>Iſrael</hi> in that Text; how much doth it concern us to maintain Juſtice and Righteouſneſs amongſt us?</p>
            <p>Indeed Juſtice is the ſoul of a Common-wealth, it lives no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then that is duly adminiſtred: And Deſolation follows in that Chapter, where Oppreſſion went before. <hi>Of a truth many houſes ſhall be deſolate, even great and fair without Inhabitant,</hi> at the 9. Verſe of the Chapter. And therefore
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:153008:71"/>what a bleſſing is returned, when Juſtice is returned to us, and brought home to our doors by wiſe and learned Judges? <hi>I will reſtore thy judges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And thy counſellors too.</hi> We muſt not leave them out, becauſe they are put into the Text; for Counſel is as neceſſary as Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſo are the <hi>Counſellors too. In the multitude of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors there is ſafety; Solomon</hi> was a wiſe Prince, and he knew it; and if his Son <hi>Rehoboam</hi> had fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed his Counſel, and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice which the old men gave him, the ten Tribes had not ſo eaſily revolted from him as they did. <hi>But I have counſel and ſtrength for the War,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Kin. 18.20.</note> and they were not vain words, though the King of <hi>Aſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi> ſaid they were; for all his great Army was able to do King <hi>Hezekiah</hi> no hurt. <hi>But if it be a Nation void of Counſel,</hi> as God complained of his people there,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:153008:71"/>
               <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.28. 'tis no wonder if they be deſtined to ruine by and by. <hi>Therefore I will reſtore thy counſellors,</hi> is an argument that God meant to preſerve them; for counſel is before ſtrength in the Judgement of King <hi>Hezekiah</hi> in that place.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Et conſiliarios tuos,</hi> at this time calls for another Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the words; for there is not onely the Kings Learned Counſel, but the Judges Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, and the Peoples Counſel too. I doubt they are not all Reſtored as the Text ſayes here, for we have ſeen the faces of ſome of them before now. But whether they be or no, good counſel is not to be refuſed, what ever the perſons be; for there is need of them, and we cannot be without them: For when God ſayes, I will take away the Honourable man and the Counſeller, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended it as a heavy Judgement
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:153008:72"/>upon <hi>Iſrael,</hi> even when there was no Counſeller, <hi>That when I asked, could anſwer a word, Iſa.</hi> 41.28.</p>
            <p>But firſt there is the Judges Counſel or his Aſſiſtants, which you will, and there is a full Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of them, <hi>Conſiliarios tuos ſicut antiquitus,</hi> a Bench full of Juſtices again, perſons of Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency in their Country, and to whom we owe the Peace of it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, there are the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Counſel, their Counſell learned in the Law, Counſellors they are called who are able to Counſel them in the Chamber, and to ſpeak for them at the Bar.</p>
            <p>I know there be ſome Phana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical people, who, as they would take away all Judges and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, ſo they would take away all Counſellors too; Enemies to all Profeſsions and Callings of men. They would preach them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and ſo they would plead themſelves too. The long Robe
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:153008:72"/>is a faſhion they like not, and the Lawyers Gowns, as well as the Canonical Coats, are an Eye-ſore to them. If ſuch mens Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes miſcarry before the Judges, they muſt thank themſelves, while they prevaricate againſt their wills, and, for want of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the Law, give the Cauſe they would defend. We cannot rank theſe among the <hi>Conſiliarios tuos</hi> in the Text; they be their own Counſellors, and not thine; and if they periſh by their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, who can help it?</p>
            <p>But thy Counſellors are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to be men of knowledge in their profeſsion, ſuch as ſpeak not without book, but are able to give counſel to them that aske it of them.</p>
            <p>And I wiſh they would give it to thoſe that are poor and indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and have nothing to give for it: <hi>But ſuch as I have I give thee.</hi> Alas! <hi>Silver and Gold they
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:153008:73"/>have none,</hi> and to them they that give their Counſel without it, would have never the leſs.</p>
            <p>But Counſellors are a bleſſing to a Nation as well as Judges, yet not every Counſellor neither nor every Judge; for both have their Qualifications in the Text, <hi>I will give thee judges as at the firſt, and counſellors as at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sicut fuerunt prius,</hi> and <hi>Sicut antiquitus;</hi> this muſt make us to look back to the beginning. And there we find very good Judges indeed, and very good Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, <hi>Moſes, Joſhua,</hi> and <hi>Samuel,</hi> ſuch Judges were able to make it a Golden Age wherein they lived, and ſuch Counſellors as they had. <hi>Moſes</hi> tells <hi>Jethro</hi> his Father in law, his manner of judging; <hi>When they have a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they come unto me, and I judge between one and another, and I make them know the Statutes of
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:153008:73"/>God, and his Lawes, Exod.</hi> 18.16. If Gods Lawes be the ſtandard, you may be ſure the Judgement cannot be amiſſe. A Judge he was that preferred the peoples ſafety before his own. <hi>Salus po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli,</hi> it was the Supreme Law with him. And therefore he cryes out to God, <hi>Dele me, Blot me out of the Book rather then theſe, Exod.</hi> 32.32. And ſo <hi>Joſhua</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded him in his care and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the people; who, among other ſignes of his good Government, made the Sun ſtand ſtill in <hi>Gibeon,</hi> and God hearkned to the voice of a man, as 'tis there, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 10.13. <hi>Till the people had avenged themſelves of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</hi> And for <hi>Samuel</hi> to omit the reſt that came between, for the time would fail me to tell of <hi>Gedeon,</hi> and of <hi>Barak,</hi> and of <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> and of the reſt of them, as the Apoſtle to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> ſpeaks of the Judges, but for <hi>Samuel,</hi>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:153008:74"/>how doth he challenge the world to lay any thing that looks like Corruption to his charge? <hi>Whoſe Oxe have I taken, or of whom have I received any Bribe?</hi> Witneſſe againſt me, they could not. And though it were an Aſſe laden with Gold he could not enter where he was, and therefore a Golden Age it muſt be ſtill. And ſo for the Counſellors to ſuch Judges, no doubt they knew all of them to make a good choice of them, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did for himſelf by the advice of <hi>Iethro,</hi> men fearing God and hating Covetouſneſſe. As 'twas ſaid of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea</hi> afterward, Honourable Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors they were.</p>
            <p>Such were the Judges and Counſellors before, and how much they were degenerated af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward, we have a ſad account of it in this Chapter but three Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes before my Text, <hi>Thy Princes are Companions of Thieves. Omnes
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:153008:74"/>diligunt munera, Every one loveth gifts, and followeth after rewards, they judge not the Fatherleſs, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth the Cauſe of the Widow come before them.</hi> Why ſuch Judges would be fley'd, be it ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with Reverence to thoſe that are not ſuch, as <hi>Cambyſes</hi> is ſaid to have ſerved ſuch a one. But if good Judges may be reſtored in their places, <hi>Ut fuerunt prius,</hi> and <hi>ſicut antiquitus,</hi> what a bleſſing muſt this be? When the poor man need not thank his good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, that he took the Judge in a good moode, <hi>Gaudeat de bona for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuna,</hi> as <hi>Montaigne</hi> ſayes, 'twas wont to be a by-word with them in <hi>France,</hi> and when the Judge doth not write too often in the Margin of his book, <hi>Caſus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amico,</hi> a Caſe for a friend, as he ſayes one did, as often as <hi>Bartolus</hi> and <hi>Boldus</hi> could not agree upon the point, and left the Caſe doubtful. But he will own no
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:153008:75"/>friend at all, nor relation upon the Bench, <hi>Point perſonam amici,</hi> he hath no friend then, but he is like <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> without Father, or Mother, or Children, or Friends, this is <hi>Sicut erant prius,</hi> one of the old Judges, whom God ſends as a bleſſing to the people.</p>
            <p>And ſo for the old Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, they were alwaies <hi>Conſiliarii pacis,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> calls them, <hi>Prov.</hi> 12.20. <hi>Counſellors of peace,</hi> they did not encourage their Neighbours or their Clients in going to Law, but they laboured to compoſe their differences; all their Counſels and Diſcourſes were <hi>Apta temperandis animis,</hi> as <hi>Druſus</hi> his in <hi>Tacitus</hi> were: they drove to a reconciliation ſtill, they did not make the Rent wider, and for that they had joy in their own Conſciences, as 'tis there. He that doth otherwiſe is none of the old Counſellors.</p>
            <pb n="143" facs="tcp:153008:75"/>
            <p>No more is he that will not ſpeak in a good Cauſe without exceſſe rewards. I am not ſo ſevere as the Senate was under <hi>Tyberius,</hi> when they called for <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gem cinciam,</hi> wherein Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates were to plead for nothing, and they would not have them <hi>Vendere operam,</hi> or have <hi>Vocem venalem.</hi> No, I know that Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence and Knowledge in the Law doth not <hi>Gratuito contingere,</hi> as 'twas urged then, it did not coſt them nothing, and that <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latis ſtudiorum pretiis etiam ſtudia peritura,</hi> without Rewards Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions will come to nothing. But yet after a long debate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Tyberius,</hi> as the reſult was in <hi>Tacitus, Capiendis pecuniis poſuit modum,</hi> ſo I would have a Meane ſet for Fees, leſt otherwiſe the Remedy prove worſe then the Diſeaſe; and a man were better loſe his right, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tac. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. lib.</hi> 10.</note> then go about to recover it. As he tells of one <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius</hi>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:153008:76"/>a Gentleman of <hi>Rome,</hi> who, when he had given his Lawyer <hi>Quadringenta Nummorum millia,</hi> I will not Engliſh it, for the ill uſe that may be made of it, and when he found at laſt he had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varicated the Cauſe too, he kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led himſelf in his Lawyers Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. That was but a ſad Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrophe of a Law ſuit, and I think I have heard of ſomething like it. But you will all juſtifie me ſo far, if any man exceed this way, and that many do; 'tis too notorious, 'tis not <hi>ſicut antiquitus,</hi> if you look back but thirty or forty yeares ſince; I think then no ſuch Rewards were heard of. And you cannot ſay this is <hi>Vetus querela,</hi> becauſe 'tis a Modern offence. But it would be reformed, leſt otherwiſe we do <hi>Portum Eloquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia ſalutarem aperire piratis,</hi> as <hi>Quintilian</hi> ſayes, make the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of Eloquence a harbour for Thieves and Robbers, and that
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:153008:76"/>we may make good the promiſe of God in the Text, <hi>Conſiliarios tuos, ſicut antiquitus, I will reſtore thy counſellors as at the beginning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will not tell you, 'tis the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of theſe abuſes in the practice of the Law, but in other things, that which God makes the ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard to reform by here in the Text, is made the great ſtone of offence; that in matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion 'tis ſo I am ſure. If you tell them of <hi>ſicut fuerunt prius,</hi> and <hi>ſicut antiquitus,</hi> of any things that were uſed heretofore; why, <hi>Eo nomine,</hi> as we uſe to ſay, it ſhall be rejected for Popery and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, and I know not what.</p>
            <p>We will have nothing that's Old. But we muſt tell them who were Conſuls, the Moneth and the day, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sacr. Eccl. Hiſt. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 29.</note> and then write <hi>Edita eſt fides Catholica,</hi> Such a year their new Religion began, as <hi>Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> complains of the <hi>Arrians</hi> in the Eccleſiaſtical ſtory. So no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:153008:77"/>but new things pleaſe this new generation of men; <hi>Quaſi now veteris Dei pudeat,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tert. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 8.</note> ſayes <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian:</hi> Why ſo we may be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of God Almighty, becauſe he is called the <hi>Ancient of dayes.</hi> The truth is, Antiquity muſt be the ſtandard, as I ſaid but now, when all's done: <hi>From the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it was not ſo,</hi> our Saviour brings them to that in the matter of Divorce. And ſo <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſayes, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>In quantum falſum corruptio eſt veri, in tantum praecedat neceſſe eſt veritas falſum;</hi> Becauſe fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhood is the corruption of truth, therefore truth muſt go before falſhood: And <hi>Illud optimum quod primum</hi> was his rule, The earlier the truer every thing muſt be. Therefore <hi>ſicut antiquitus</hi> ſhould be no ſcandal to ſober men. <hi>But I conſidered the dayes of old, and the years that are paſt,</hi> ſayes <hi>David;</hi> for they will be the beſt Counſellors for other
<pb facs="tcp:153008:77"/>things, and therefore no bad ones for the Counſellors themſelves.</p>
            <p>Well, ſay what we will, <hi>ut fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt prius</hi> and <hi>ſicut antiquitus,</hi> are a bleſsing upon a Nation. We know what it means, <hi>Res novas moliri,</hi> and we have no reaſon to be in love with Innovations for their ſakes; we have payed dear for our News. But now <hi>ſicut anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitus,</hi> to ſee the old face of things reſtored, to ſee <hi>Judges as at the firſt, and Counſellors as at the beginning;</hi> the good old Juſtices I mean, as well as the old Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, if there be any of them left, to ſee Juſtice run in the old Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel again, (for though we might have it before, yet the courſe of the ſtream was altered, and many times it ran over the banks) to hear <hi>Carolus Dei gratia</hi> in the Commiſsion again, inſtead of <hi>Cuſtodes libertatis,</hi> (and how they kept it we all know) or inſtead of ſome body that was worſe, if
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:153008:78"/>worſe might be; how muſt this revive the hearts, and chear up the ſpirits, of honeſt men?</p>
            <p>For I will confeſs to you, in our late diſpenſations of Juſtice, for my own particular, I never took any comfort at all; when the Judges and Juſtices them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves methought looked like ſo many guilty perſons, and a man could hardly tell which were the greateſt offendors, whether they, of the Priſoners that ſtood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them. But Juſtice, I know, was neceſſary howſoever, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they brought that, they are to be excuſed.</p>
            <p>But now we have <hi>judices ut fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erunt prius,</hi> and <hi>conſiliarios ſicut antiquitus,</hi> the Kings Judges and Juſtices again; King <hi>Charles</hi> his Judges, as venerable as Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Knights were wont to be; like old Okes, <hi>quae non tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam habent ſpeciem, quantam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionem,</hi> as <hi>Quintillian</hi> ſayes;
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:153008:78"/>and they diſpenſe Juſtice to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry body that defires it. And this is as great a bleſsing as a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is capable of; for now</p>
            <p>Juſtice gives a Denomination to the People themſelves, and to the Community that are made up of them; ſo we have it in the cloſe of the Text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Poſthac vocaberis civit as juſtitiae, urbs fidelis, Afterward thou ſhalt be called the city of righteouſneſs, the faithful city.</hi> What they were or might be called before with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out juſtice, I told you before, even no better then a City of Robbers, a Den of Thieves: But now they have a new name, <hi>The city of righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There was a King of that name in Scripture, <hi>Melchiſedech, The King of righteouſneſs,</hi> ſo the word ſignifies, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.2. And here's a People like their King, <hi>A City of righteouſneſſe</hi> too. Or <hi>the City of the righteous man, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitas
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:153008:79"/>juſti,</hi> in the Vulgar Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation, The City of the juſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, of <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> as I ſaid but now, or the King of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: for the King of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe muſt be a righteous and juſt King, elſe that Name had not been proper for him.</p>
            <p>And that King was Chriſt, <hi>The juſt one,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſo we find him called, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.14. <hi>Ye have denyed the holy and the juſt one: He that was a Prieſt for ever after the order of Melchiſedech;</hi> and ſo after his order he was a righteous King too; and the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhall be called after his name, <hi>A city of righteouſneſſe.</hi> But then as Chriſt vouchſafes his other Titles to Kings, <hi>Dixi, Dii eſtis, I have ſaid, Ye are Gods;</hi> and <hi>Touch not my Chriſts:</hi> ſo he will not deny them this, Every righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous King is a <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> a King of righteouſneſs, and his Dominions ſhall be called <hi>Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:153008:79"/>juſti, The City of the righteous man;</hi> or from the influence which a good King hath over his Subjects, <hi>the City of righteouſneſs</hi> it ſelf: For by themſelves alone Kings cannot be righteous, but every body elſe will follow the faſhion. And <hi>Civitas</hi> here is not Latine for the Kings Court onely, or his Palace, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed may be well called the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of righteouſneſſe, where the King is a juſt Prince; but this Righteouſneſſe is diffuſed fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<q>—Regis ad exemplum,—</q> even to all the People, and 'tis now a City of righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>What happineſs may not ſuch a City promiſe it ſelf? We have read or heard of an <hi>Utopia,</hi> or <hi>Plato</hi>'s Commonwealth, and ſome men are apt to dream of it; no Government will pleaſe them but that, where Angels muſt dwell inſtead of Men, for
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:153008:80"/>there muſt be no faults nor er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors in the Government. Here's the place they wot of, not in a fiction but in truth; for 'tis in righteouſneſſe here. Since the old Judges and Counſellors are reſtored, they ſhall be called <hi>the City of righteouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what name can be more proper, where Juſtice is duly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred, and mens Properties are preſerved, and Invaders of other mens Rights puniſhed, and the Oppreſsions of the Widows and Fatherleſſe redreſſed, and there is no <hi>Complaining in the ſtreets,</hi> as 'tis in the Pſalme? 'tis a <hi>City of righteouſneſs</hi> you may be ſure, and the People are happy that live in it.</p>
            <p>To be free of ſome Cities ſome men will give much; <hi>With a great ſumme obtained I this free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> ſaid the Chief Captaine to Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and yet 'twas but to be a Free-man of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:153008:80"/>which was no City of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe neither, eſpecially under ſuch an Emperour as <hi>Claudius</hi> or <hi>Nero.</hi> What would one give to be free of this City? as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was there, to be <hi>born free, A City wherein dwelleth righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe,</hi> as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks of that City which is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and wherein righteous men dwell.</p>
            <p>'Tis in us beloved to make it a City of Righteouſneſſe here, and a Heaven upon Earth. 'Tis not in the King alone, though he be a <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> a King of Righteouſneſſe, as I told you: Nor in the Judges nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, though they be never ſo Righteous themſelves, nor in the Juſtices and Counſellors, though they be <hi>ſicut antiquitus,</hi> Reformed never ſo much; yet if the people be the ſame they were, 'tis they that denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate the City; and 'tis moſt
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:153008:81"/>uſuall for them to complain of unrighteouſneſſe and bad times, who themſelves make them ſo. But 'tis in us I ſay to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme our ſelves, and to make it a City of Righteouſneſſe. Great advantages we have, and encouragements by a Righteous King, and good Judges and Counſellors to make us Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous. But if they be <hi>ſicut antiquitus,</hi> and we be not ſo, but <hi>ſicut heri,</hi> and we will be of the new Mode ſtill, and as we were, we muſt thank our ſelves, if it be not a City of Righteouſneſſe. Well, <hi>He that is unjuſt, let him be unjuſt ſtill;</hi> but if we be ſo, we muſt look to bear the blame of it, for fruſtrating Gods deſigne in the Text, which is to make us <hi>A ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>a faithfull city too. Urbs fidelis,</hi> this is the laſt circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and it comes near us
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:153008:81"/>indeed. 'Tis above Verſe 21. <hi>How is the faithfull city become an Harlot?</hi> It implies, as if we had been unfaithfull before. The <hi>Septuagint</hi> read it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the faithfull <hi>Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis</hi> or Mother City. I know not how that word came in; but it tempts me to ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which I muſt not, for the very many righteous perſons ſakes that were in it, even then when the times were at the worſt. I will not therefore look back: But for the future I will Propheſie better, becauſe I have warrant for it in the Text, <hi>Voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beris Urbs fidelis, Thou ſhalt be call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the faithful city.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The brand of Infidelity eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to a lawfull King, as it is moſt odious, ſo the Title of faithfulneſs is moſt glorious. <hi>Vocaberis Urbs fidelis, Thou ſhalt be called the faithful city;</hi> it ſhould be written upon the Gates of
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:153008:82"/>them that were ſo, and it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves to ſtand upon Record to the Eternall Honour of them, and of this poor City in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, that durſt own the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the King, even then, when He was going to the Block.</p>
            <p>But now every City ſhall be ſo called, faithful to their Prince, and faithful to their God too: faithful to their God in the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the firſt Table, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to their Prince in thoſe of the ſecond.</p>
            <p>And ſo we ſhall be called a faithful City, and we ſhall ſhew the world our Faith by our Works, as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> would have us, by our Obedience to the King, and by our juſt deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and Righteouſneſs one towards another: And for this God will reward us, and carry us from this City of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and faithfulneſs here,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:153008:82"/>to his Kingdom of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whither we beſeech him to bring us all, for the Merits of his Son Chriſt Ieſus; To whom, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
